Nevertheless, God is good.
And so we unite ourselves with the good confession of the three young men.
And together with them, our good confession will echo through eternity,
and we will not be ashamed.
Glory to God.
And that was Father Stephen Freeman with Glory to God.
Father Stephen is the priest at St. Anne Orthodox Church in Oak Ridge, Tennessee,
and hosts the Glory to God for all things blog site.
which can be accessed from his podcast site at ancientfaithradio.com.
This is a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever,
you're listening to ancientfaithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous,
with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations
the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
Firstenach, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat,
secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is-
this spiritual reality like.
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life
with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung,
post this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers and
dragon slayers. You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast. My co-host Father Stephen D'Yung
is with me on location from Franklin, Tennessee. That's right, you're Nashville.
And I'm following state in the land of the free. Is it really? That's what I'm told.
That's what they tell you. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So I'm Father Andrew Stephen D'Yemek and
Emmaus Pennsylvania, the Forests of Penn. And if you're listening to us live, you can call in
855 AF radio that's 855237234
6.
Matziskotruti is taking your calls tonight and this episode is all Q&A.
So get calling right now.
You don't have to wait.
Get your plays in line right now.
But first a word from our sponsor.
Lord of Spirits is brought to you by our listeners with help from the Theoria School of
Filmmaking.
Theoria School of Filmmaking is the first Orthodox film school.
The primary instructor is Jonathan Jackson, a faithful Orthodox Christian speaker, writer,
5-time Emmy Award winner to learn more
about theorya please visit theoryafilm.org that's THERIAAfilm.org. So tonight in addition
to being an all Q&A episode this is our special second anniversary episode happy anniversary
to us. It's hard to believe we've been at this for two years to mark this occasion.
So technically, technically,
text not an all Q&A episode.
Oh, that's true.
Because like...
What we're about to play is neither a Q nor an A.
That is yeah.
Well, I don't know.
It depends on a live one.
Yes, true.
Yeah.
So anyway, to mark this occasion,
we're going to be playing three special clips of some of our favorite memories.
And we'll be playing one in each of our three halves.
So, Father Stephen,
while all those calls are queuing up,
should we go ahead and play the first one?
We probably should.
And, you know...
We went back and forth on doing this because I mean it's only two years of shows these are pretty memorable clips
I'm sure people have already heard these and relisted to them like a thousand times. Yeah
Yeah, these are just some of our favorites. Yeah, I mean right. I mean, it's so hard to pick right
We just had to pick a few that were
Super memorable the kind that are already on t-shirts and stuff
Yeah, it's like choosing between your children and we all know all parents have a favorite kid
I
don't. I love all four of mine absolutely equally.
Alive.
Anyway, all right. Well, so here is our first half of memory clip
that we're going to play for you.
Okay, we're going to go ahead and take a call right now. And the
call board says I have Jonathan calling from Montreal. So
Jonathan welcomes the Lord of Spirit.
podcast are you there?
Yes, hello, father.
This is actually it's John calling not from Montreal in Sicily.
So yeah, it's a little further away.
But I really love the show.
You know, I first time in call but I have a question.
It's a question I'm asking for a friend.
So it's really actually more with speculative questions.
Okay.
So let's say, just for theory sake, let's say that you...
situation where you had a clot
Alephicon, like just let's say for
theory sake. How do you think you
would go about getting him to give
you the pot of gold because the
catch. I might the idea would be
that you think that catching him
would be the hardest but it seems
like the pot of gold question is
harder. So I don't know if you
have any advice on that. So you're
asking like for a friend, this is
for a friend.
What's like a theoretical question for a friend, really?
Okay, so the first question I have in response to this is exactly how is this accomplished?
I mean, I'm, you know, there's a lot of, which there's a lot of ways to catch a leprechaun.
Okay, I mean, you can use a standard bear trap, you know, you can.
Yeah.
I think you're, I think what I hear that you're supposed to listen for the sound of like a metal
hammer.
because because because the
polarity is leprechauns
they make shoes for L. So
if you hear that in the
fourth and you know that
it's nearby and then it's
just I mean then you just
can wrestle it to the
ground. I mean the nail
is sharp though. It's not
easy. So are you saying
that leprechauns basically
function for L. Is the way
that that dwarves do for
humans and giants and so
forth. That there's sort
of like a mess kind of yeah.
Yeah. Okay. Well, I mean,
the here's the first tip
that I would give you is
number one, don't feed
feed it and don't eat with it.
Because if you listen to this podcast at all, you know that that's a huge huge problem. So just don't do that right all right
That's that's the first thing that I just said. I don't know father Steven do you have any
Anything more to say about that. Well, it's it's interesting because of course, you know the leprechaun right is doing this work
Out of its love for the craft right because it has the ponder
Right, it's not true a working class creature, right
right right right left out of
It's love for its craft and the craftsmanship, right?
And so to me that says, right?
To me that says, the pot of gold, I mean, it's somewhere.
It's safety.
It's backup, right?
So it's maybe not as precious to the leprechaun
as it would be to an averageous human.
So I would think if you could present a good case
to the leprecha.
Right?
You could explain sort of comparative economics between reason with it between the Feywild, right? The fairy folk and
You know, I can do this.
Jews like Italian Jews, God, and it is really right. So you get them good shoots. Right. Like and and human economics
He would see that that pot of gold is gonna be much more valuable to you than it is to him
Right, and he could continue then you'll let him go right after you get the gold
he could go back to his craft.
which he loves, you'll have the gold. It's a win-win.
Everybody wins. That's what I've been saying. But I think I will definitely take that advice
and we'll see. I think the theoretical, yeah, we'll see. So thank you so much for your advice
and for your wonderful podcast. Thanks for calling in and tell all your friends.
All right, bye-bye.
All right. That really brought me back.
Yeah, that question of course is what inspired
our leprechaun episode. Yeah. Oh yeah.
Totally. It's a big off point. Right.
Cause there's just a huge amount to talk about there.
I actually had to do a lot of research for that one in my my my Celtic
mythology books. So yeah. I know. See, at first, you know, I suggested,
hey, let's just do a whole leprechaun episode. And you were like, well,
I saw leprechaun in the hood. And I'm like, that doesn't count. Oh,
right. That's not even the best leprechaun movie. That's not even the one with
Jennifer Aniston in it.
like why would you use that as your basis?
So did you know that Jennifer Aniston was raised orthodox?
Just putting out that.
Oh, well she is Greek anyway.
So actually, I don't know that she was raised orthodox,
but she is Greek.
So all right, well, we're taking calls.
So we're going to go ahead and just start knocking
out some calls.
So we have Jim calling from, at least his phone is from Florida.
Jim, are you there?
I am fathers.
Please bless.
God bless you.
Welcome, Jim, to Lord of Spirits, all Q and A podcast.
how
you this evening. I'm doing well thank you so much for this show. It has
redeemed so much of the Bible for me. Oh awesome awesome and although I am from
Florida, I don't have any crazy Florida man questions. This is going back kind of
to the Fall of Man part three episodes. Okay. Where you have as creation was
initially ordered you had the angels who were charged with overseeing the
different nations.
And as the angels fell and men fell, that kind of, that had to adapt and change.
Their scope of work had to adapt and change.
And so nowadays, we have the saints kind of doing that function because we have heavenly,
heavenly patrons of different cities and countries.
And so they're not really replacing the angels, but they're functioning in that original
capacity that they were ordered to do in the heavenly kingdom.
which I think is part of God's promise to Abraham,
the descendants would be like these stars.
Right.
And that we would expect
an implore the saints will continue to perform
more and more angel-like functions.
And I'm not suggesting that we turn into angels by nature,
but that we're becoming more like them.
But my question is
kind of going back to the
fall like you had the five falls of the angels, the three falls of men. What is there in place,
as any of the fathers addressed anything about the potential for angels to fall again, or then
for us to fall again? Okay, I think I get what you're asking that, are we going to see potentially
more angels go bad than are currently bad, right?
And could we directly see a saint go bad? Is that what you're asking?
Yes, yes sir.
Okay, okay, I think that makes sense to me.
I don't, and maybe Father Stephen you remember, but I don't recall exactly who said this.
I feel like Saint John de Damascus made of addressed it.
But there is this idea that God is preventing any further false from angels
and human beings once...
they participate in that first resurrection, right?
So once they actually become fully saints,
that they are also then preserved by grace
from doing that as well.
But so that's my understanding.
I don't know if father am I,
am I misremembering where that comes from?
I think, I'm not sure what exactly you're trying,
the quote is that you're,
but St. John Damascus does address that idea.
Yeah.
So yeah, contra the prophecy movies.
the first one being the only good luck,
which Christopher Wacken plays the archangelic.
Correct.
Contra those, right, there will be neither further
edgelic or human falls, but for different reasons.
So in the case of humans,
we have to remember what Adam's position was, right?
And so this is why in the first episode
we talked about the falls of humanity.
even though it kind of sounded like taking a shot at St. Augustine, we pointed out that
Adam wasn't like perfect. He was not in a state of perfection. He was in a state of innocence.
Right. So Adam was at the beginning of a journey that would lead him to become what the
saints have become. Right. And so because he was at that beginning point,
Bye.
that innocent but very mutable point, right?
He was able to fall.
Now does it make sense?
By saints we refer to as, for example,
the spirits of the righteous made perfect.
Being made complete or made mature
or who have come to their end sort of their tell us, right?
And so the state of a redeemed human
is different in a bunch of ways from the state of Apple.
them. Right. And so that's why for humans, that that kind of fall will not be possible. So
it's a little different within Sherlock beings. Part of this goes back to we don't know what it's
like to be a bat or a fast cosmic intelligence. Right. That their experience of time is different
for Mars. Right. And.
So this is why even though we had to go into some wibbly, wobbly,
timey, whimy stuff and phenomenology,
we talked about how the fall of the angels
if looked at from the top down and some of the fathers
say this, looked at from the top down sort of happened
instantly at their creation.
But looked at from our human perspective that if
enters into our human consciousness and knowledge
at different points in our history.
And so what we have at the scriptures
is from the human perspective,
not from an angelic perspective.
And if it was from God's perspective,
none of us will be able to understand it, right?
In the sense that, right, right,
we're not capable of comprehending things
as God comprehends things, right?
So when we talk about the five-ish falls of the angels, we're talking about how that
enters into human history and their interactions with humanity and how those angelic falls come
into play in the human falls.
But we're not saying this is how angels experience it.
Yeah, we don't know that.
to suggest like the movie prophecy,
which is gonna see a spike in viewership.
after this episode, I'm sure.
The King make angels could follow the future.
One of the presuppositions there is that they're sort of like us,
and they're experiencing time the way we are.
And they're just sort of immortal humans, right?
And therefore, on any given day, they can decide to sin, right?
But that's projecting what it is to be human onto an angel.
We're imagining ourselves,
If we were just sort of immortal and had
and lived in the sky, right?
Which is not what an angel is.
Right, right.
Right.
Does that make sense, Jim?
That makes excellent sense.
Excellent. All right.
Well, thanks very much for calling
into the Lord of Spears podcast.
Okay, it's an all-Q&A episode.
So we're just going to keep going.
So next we have William calling.
William, welcome to the Lord of Spears podcast.
What's on your mind?
Thank you, fathers.
What's on my mind is...
The question of the branch theory of the church and Israel.
So, very small non-controversial topic.
So, it's a bit of a long question.
I've heard some contemporary Protestants giving the scent of the branch theory of the
church by pointing to Israel being divided both into a northern kingdom but both being God's
people.
And obviously, as Orthodox Christians, we reject the branch theory.
But the difference.
The business Israel is strange because the Bible does seem to refer to both Northern and
Southern as his people, and nevertheless, there seems to exist a real gist in between the two of them.
It seems to me that one of the two sins that came to Halcaphat is trying to act like there
is no schism between Northern and Southern when there clearly is.
I've read St. Capriens' Defense of the United Church where he differentiates old Israel from
the church by saying, a hitches 2 niggas, 2 niggas, 2 niggas, 2 niggas.
Christ to never remain tall so the church will not be defided.
And I'll be honest that doesn't make it kind of sense to me.
So my question is, if we, as Orthodox Christians say that Israel is the church, how do we understand
that Israel had a real schism or both sides seem to be God's people with varying degrees
of faithfulness.
honest name particularly interested in how this relates to how we understand.
Roman Catholics and the non-Calfidonians. Yeah, yeah. So I mean, it's a good question. And you know,
I'll answer kind of from the angle of the way that the the consulior tradition and the church
fathers treat schism, right? So they definitely condemn it for sure. There is occasionally you will see
Some of them say that there's damnation on the other side of a schism, but actually you know...
see that very often. For instance, what you see in the
conciliar texts is much more like what you see in St. Paul,
where he talks about handing someone over to Satan so that for
the sake of his salvation, right, that's what a Nathema is
actually for. It's supposed to be ultimately therapeutic for
someone's salvation. And the thing that I'll add, and that
doesn't mean by the way that schism doesn't do anything or that
it isn't real, but that the question of who exactly is the people
God and
who isn't the people of God,
is kind of in some sense the wrong question.
Because the question really is,
how does everyone become part of the body of Christ?
That's always the motive for the church fathers,
that's what they call the sotereological motive,
like how can everyone be saved?
Now that doesn't make them universalist,
but that's the motivation.
Right?
So, the problem with looking at a schism,
even an old one, and saying,
well, this definitely means that...
This one side is completely inside Christ,
and this other side is completely outside of Christ,
is defining exactly when that happens, right?
So for instance, right now in the Orthodox Church,
there are schisms between churches.
There are churches that are out of communion with each other
within what we would all recognize
as being the Orthodox Church.
That is a reality.
Does that mean that one side of that is outside of the
Orthodox Church and the other side is inside it?
What about the fact that some are in communion
with some of the same parties as each other.
right? So it's not very cut and dry when you try to use the lines of schism to define who is the
people of God and who is not the people of God, especially because ultimately, as it says in
scripture, everyone's going to be judged according to his works. And the point at which it really
matters whether you're in the church is at the end of time when it will finally be truly revealed
when everyone truly is in Christ or there's going to be some who are out.
that of Christ, right? That's that possibility exists. So that doesn't mean that every single person who calls himself Christian
is
equally within the church, right? But that especially when we're dealing with it in this present life, it can be kind of difficult to
define exactly
Who is in and who is out because we're moving along the timeline, right?
What is clearer is for instance you've got the commandment from St. Basil of Priests
He says, you know, do not consult.
with whom it is forbidden, right? That's very direct. And you know, you see that reflected in
the canons of the councils don't concelebrate with whom it is forbidden. Well, who's doing the
forbidden? Forbidden. It's your bishop. He's the one doing the forbidding, right? So you have to obey
him when he says that. So, you know, someone should not listen to everything I just said and say,
well, you know, Father, Interest, even, Damex thinks that schism doesn't do anything. I mean,
certainly like, seeing the nation of Antioch has very strong things to say about it. But also,
while saying you know it's not over until it's over.
We don't really know the effect of a schism until it's truly, truly over.
And it's not truly over.
We're still in the Messianic age, right?
So I don't know if that money is the water at all or if that helps.
But at least that's from the kind of the looking at it from what the
ecumenical councils actually do say about it, right?
The motive always is how do we heal this?
Not how do we say who's out and who's in?
You know, even when you look upon people that are clearly heretics, for instance, to deny
the divinity of the Holy Spirit, for instance, St. Gregory the Theologian in one of his
orations talks about people who deny the divinity of the Holy Spirit.
And he praises them and goes on and on and on and says, I really wish that we could worship
together.
I admire all of these things that you do, you know, and so forth.
That should be the attitude.
So I don't know, a father's Stephen, what would you add to that or...
comment on that or I'm actually about that based on what William is saying, especially about
the division of the Northern and Southern Kingdom of Israel.
So part of the way this question discussed is really frayed with a lot of our Protestant
friends because they have as a pre-supposition that being a Christian, being a member of the Church.
and being quote unquote saved.
That's a Venn diagram that is one big circle, right?
Like those three things mean the same thing
for a lot of our Protestant friends.
And for us, those do not mean the same thing.
Yeah, right?
Those three terms can identify different groups of people
and there's an overlap in the Venn diagram.
But it's done.
100% and so you can see this really clearly with the example of ancient Israel, right?
In that sure, both the northern kingdom and the southern kingdom are still referred to as God's
people, but that in five bucks gets you a cup of coffee at Starbucks, right? If these
serians were there massacring you because you had spent the entire existence of your nation
at best worship.
being Yahweh in a pagan way alongside other gods at worst,
worshipping Bale instead.
The fact that you were part of one of the tribes that came out
of Egypt would avail you absolutely nothing.
In fact, St. Paul tells us in Romans 2 that those people
faced a stoner judgment because they had the revelation
of God unlike the other nations.
Right? So, uh, yeah.
Ed and as St. Paul quotes from the Old Testament, not all in Israel are of Israel.
So there are lots of people who are part of God's people in the Old Testament,
the sense that there are Israelites who did not experience what we would call salvation,
who were apostates. And the same is true in the Church today.
We all continue to work out our salvation because we don't want to be one of them.
but the fact that you got that
baptized in an Orthodox church, you know, and maybe got married in one and maybe get buried out of one. That doesn't necessarily mean you found salvation.
And that doesn't necessarily depending on how you lived your life, even mean that you're a Christian.
These are separate categories.
So I could look at someone who's not part of the Orthodox Church
and acknowledge whether or not they're a Christian,
whether they're trying to follow Christ as best they know how.
But by saying, yeah, I consider that person to be a Christian.
I'm not saying they're part of the church because they're not part of the Orthodox Church.
And I'm not making any judgment about whether they're experiencing theosis,
their relationship with God, what that is, how they'll fare at the final judgment.
I'm making no presuppositions about that whatsoever when I say that.
And likewise, when I say somewhat some member of the Orthodox Church,
If I don't know them, I don't know that they're living a Christian life or not, and I get...
and I'm not making any judgment about their salvation, right?
So for us, these are sort of separate categories.
And so that argument doesn't really work
because we're able to say, well, sure, there is real lights.
Israel, Judah, all those people are Israelites.
But again, that doesn't get you anything.
Yeah, I think one of the big problems with the branch theory
is that it basically says that schism is normal
doesn't have to be really doesn't.
have to be overcome. Right? I think that's really the problem with it. It's just like, well,
we're out of communion and that's okay. Right? That it's a sort of accepted as normal.
But that's, you know, that's indefensible from the Christian tradition. Really.
A schism is always a tragedy that needs to be fixed.
But it goes further than that too. Because what you have to do to hold to the branch theory is
you have to form eventually depending on how far you go with it.
you have to form this kind of lowest common denominator.
Christianity. Yeah, right. Exactly.
Where where I is a modern human decide arbitrarily what are and aren't the
really important doctrines. Yeah, just on my own authority.
Because heresy eventually goes along with schism.
Well, because even if it doesn't on day one, all these groups have legitimate
disagreements with each other, right? Theologically and otherwise.
Right, so I know people who from the
way they live their lives are very good Christian people. Some of them are even clergy in Protestant
denominations, but they not accidentally they have considered the niceing doctrine of
the Trinity and their social trinitarians, right, or some other view of the Trinity that
is at best heterodox and at worst heretical, right? I can't say, oh yeah, there's no difference
between me and them.
right? Because who God is is pretty important. Who Christ is is pretty important. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. And so by doing the branch theory thing, you're not only saying, excuse me,
it's fine, it's normal. But you're saying these differences don't matter. Which means that these
doctrines aren't important. Yeah. Heresy isn't really a thing or it's a smaller thing. You know.
had the Christian faith and the Christian way of life is something that can be broken up into pieces.
parts of it are more important than other parts and parts of it are negotiable
and none of that is something we can say is an Orthodox Christian.
Yeah. Yeah. Does that help William or does that make it all so much worse?
Um, yeah. Yes, great. Okay. It's a very learn of spirit's response.
Porky to Losto. It might just quick follow up. I'm not terribly concerned about it
and a question of salvation.
I'm concerned about it in terms of
a dissolution of what the church actually is.
Because I mean, we've talked before about the ritual participation
as defining a people as a people and the ritual participation of Israel.
And as this works, we also have the ritual participation in the church,
which branched there just rejects that possibility.
And so this gives them between northern and southern Israel.
For me, it's more of a concern that if we sit
at the Orthodox Church is Israel,
that we have been grafted into it.
But Israel itself seems to have splintered parts.
Right, let me try and clarify.
I think I get what you're asking.
So part of what we have to say here is that
the ritual and worship of the Northern Kingdom
was entirely a list
it in apostate from day one. The worship and ritual of the southern kingdom of Judah was,
you know, will be generous and say 50-50 illicit in apostate, right? The true worship was still
there and was maintained, though it was a narrow thread in the southern kingdom.
Okay? So by that standard before Israel was destroyed, the northern kingdom of Israel gets destroyed
because it is our
the apostate because of its witness. That's what the Old Testament says. Right. And so we are
grafted in as we understand what St. Paul is saying in Romans 9 through 11, we're grafted
into replace the northern tribes. The northern tribes have been dispersed into the nations, into
the Gentiles. And so the calling of the Gentiles is to reconstitute those 10 tribes. So it's not just
that we got grabbed.
in on top of the 12 tribes, our grafting in reconstitutes the 10 northern tribes, so that
as St. Paul says, at the end of Romans 11, when the time of the Gentiles is fulfilled, all Israel
will be saved, not just Judah and some Benchamites and some Levites.
Okay, so sort of like how the saints are replacing the spirits, the angels that sell.
the Gentiles are grafted in to replace the 10 tribes.
Yes. And also with the complication that the,
say, and also with the complication that the 10 tribes have been
dissolved into the nations. So when the nations come to worship Israel's God,
it is the return of the 10 tribes. Right. Yeah. Right.
Yeah. And that's what state Paul is doing with that grafting language.
If you're going to graft a branch in, you have to make a cut first.
Okay.
It makes a lot more sense.
The brains are cut off for faithlessness and that then gives a place for the faithful branches to be grafted in.
Yeah.
Alrighty.
Well, thank you very much for calling William. Good to talk to you.
Alright, well, next we have Andy and his phone at least is from Washington DC.
So Andy, welcome to the Lord's Peer's podcast.
Andy, are you there?
All right, do we lose Andy?
Okay, well, we are going to go ahead and take the next caller and hopefully we can get Andy back.
Deep state got him.
Yeah.
I know.
Well, it is watching the DC.
I mean, what can you say?
Exactly.
So yeah.
All right. Well, I think we have Zach.
Zach, are you there?
Yes, Father's, can you hear me?
Yes, we hear you.
So Zach, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
Are you still there, Zach?
Okay, go ahead.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So my question goes all the way back to the Relic episode.
Okay.
This notion of being of identity as an action
and the example that you gave Father Andrew was of the true cross
that like it that it was almost beside the point
whether that piece of wood was like
physically from the cross Christ was hung on, but because it was being
venerated and received after true cross, it was being the true cross and so is, in
a sense, the true cross. So my question with that is for someone who, like I
really, that really spoke to me and really cleared up a lot of things for me, but I
I can also see somebody be skeptical.
the point of how how being does this not lead into a sort of relative is on like a sort of
self-contradictory almost unworkable ontological and epistemic free-fuel that like we can make
anything anything just because of how we see things or think it is.
Yeah. Yeah. So I mean what I would say to that initially is.
is we don't have the power to make anything, anything.
Right.
We still have to treat things according to their nature.
Right, I can't just say, well, you're,
I can't say, well, you are now in a rangatang
because I'm gonna treat you like in a rangatang.
Like you won't, because number one,
that's not your nature, but number two,
I'm not the only person,
I'm not the only relationship that matters to your being.
you
In fact, I'm a pretty minor one when you're being is considered, right?
Because you're also in relationship to God and you're in relationship to all the other
matter that's around you and you relationship other persons around you.
And so even if every person around you says you're an orangutan, that still doesn't make
you one, right?
Because that's not your nature.
So it's not arbitrary.
It's not that anything can be anything, right?
So we had to keep that in mind.
It's not the fact that a piece of wood can be put together and said,
here's the cross of Christ, whether we say this is a relic of the true cross,
or simply this is a hand cross that I made from an oak tree in my backyard,
it still functions as the cross of Christ for us, right?
Because that's appropriate to the way it's been shaped
and that's appropriate to its nature.
But if I have a handful of just liquid water and say,
Here's the Cross of Christ.
that doesn't actually work that way because it's contrary to its nature. Now you could freeze it
and actually I've used ice crosses for doing outdoor water blessings and that becomes the cross
of Christ within that ritual context. But if it was just liquid, then no one would believe that
because that's not what it actually is. Father Stephen, you want to add a just bend?
and do you realize?
Well, yeah.
I mean, first, first.
And this is just a general statement.
A lot of things have become these sort of bug bear words,
where that sounds like relativism.
And so, oh no, no, no, no, no.
And we all know that's better.
That sounds most modern.
That sounds modern.
So we need to be careful with those words.
And if someone's criticism of an idea,
I'm not applying this to use that.
but to someone who maybe you may be interacting with.
If their sole criticism is that sounds like blank,
that's not a valid criticism.
Right.
But so part of this is, it's rather interesting
what we're able to do.
And we aren't able to flip our own phenomenology
like a switch.
Here's what I mean by that.
I can go and
shave off a piece of wood and I can go and buy a reliquary on eBay and I can put the piece of wood in it and I can
Go to my church and say hey, I got sent this
From a bishop in this country. This is a piece of the true cross and I can put it out for veneration
You know my my bishop is in town, so I'm not saying I'm going to do this
now. It is possible. But I could do that, right? And we were very much saying in that episode,
and I would still say that for the people who believe me and come and venerate it,
they are venerating the true cross of Christ. And that God's action through my phony relic
is undisturbed by the fact that it's a phony relic that I may. But...
It will never be for me the cross of Christ.
I can't trick myself into it being the cross of Christ for me.
So we were speaking at a phenomenological level,
at the level of experience and of interrelationship with specifically God's actions,
the divine energies, not at the level of untimed.
in the sense of a kind of parmenody in, right?
This is this thing, it is not any other thing, right?
So we're using identity in that phenomenal logical sense,
because as we pointed out, everything,
not just God, has an essence and has energies.
So we're not talking about what that,
what my phony piece of wood is in its essence.
We're talking about what it is in its activities and its interrelationships with people.
And everything, everything that exists has different identities and different relationships
to different people.
And so for example, in my phony relic example, it would have one relationship to the people
who come and venerate it wholeheartedly and a completely different relationship to me who
phony did up and made it into the first place.
That makes sense?
Yeah, that, yes, yes, that does.
Because that really cleared up for me was with all these phenomenal logical approaches,
is it almost seems to slip into an almost radical constructivism.
But I know you all pushed back on that in a few episodes past.
And it's more of this interaction idea between the objective real world outside of ourselves
of ourselves with
our subjective consciousness is really what reality is for us phenomenologically.
So yeah, I mean, that's just right.
How it works.
We don't have access to a, we don't have access to anything outside of our experience.
Like, that's just not as humans.
Yeah, as humans, right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So all right, well, thank you very much for calling.
We're going to go ahead and take one more call before the break.
Hopefully we have Andy back.
Andy, are you back?
I'm back, I'm here.
All right, Andy.
So you weren't swallowed by the deep state.
You fought them off.
I guess not.
No, and I'm here with my son Ezra, who is 13,
and we both enjoy listening to the podcast together.
It's really opened up.
The scriptures are both of us,
and we each have a question if that's okay.
Awesome.
All right, well, nice to be speaking with you as well, Ezra.
And so I
figured I would ask and then I'll have Ezra ask and you could answer the question.
So my question is in Matthew 16 when Jesus asked the disciples, who do people say that the
son of man is?
If you know for a first century or second century Jewish person hearing that for the
first time would they think that Jesus is about to open up a discussion about, for example,
who the figure in Daniel 7 is without necessarily referring that to himself.
And then I'm going to have my son ask a question.
Okay, go ahead.
Thank you for answering.
So I had a question about the extra books that are in the Orthodox and Catholic
Bibles, but not in the Protestant.
I was wondering like I read lots of things that Protestant people have written
Like reasons why they should not be in the Bible.
But it seems like many of those were developed after they were already taken out and I'm just wondering like the main reason they were taken out in the first place and how we can react to that and yeah.
All right, great question Ezra.
Okay, well I'm going to punt the first one over to you, Father Steven, because I'm sure that you have a lot to say about this.
Not I really.
No, okay.
Oh no.
I will. So, yeah, so in the context, right, we've already had Christ refer to
himself as the Son of Man. So this is a Porque de Olo's Doe situation. So, for the
disciples, they've already heard Christ identify himself as the Son of Man. But
But they're also, especially if you look at their answers, right, that they are.
bringing in answers that are connected to pre-existing son of man traditions in
Second Temple Judaism. Right? So for example, when they bring up Elijah or one of the
prophets, right? Like that was one of the major traditions that Elijah, because he
didn't die, right? And he was going to return often with Enoch and that that shows up in the
of Revelation. But so the
They're both implying when they say,
well, some say Elijah or one of the prophets,
they're both implying,
this is who people believe the Son of Man is,
and this is who people believe you are,
who believe that you are the Son of Man.
Does that make sense?
There's kind of a both-hand.
Yeah.
Like even if you just look at Matthew,
Christ uses the phrase Son of Man,
three-furt himself, like nine or 10 times,
even before that passage.
So
there's context. Yeah, but both ideas are being brought in. So it is good that you notice
that yeah, this has this bigger resonance than just who do people say I am, right? It's
not just a synonym for I, but it brings in these other ideas, right? As well. Yeah. To
Ezra, I want to say, first of all, long before you were born in the 90s, there was a band
called better than Ezra.
And I'm going to tell you today that I think they were lying because I think you are better than that
Even from this brief interaction we've had indeed indeed. I think you are a better man than day
And in terms of in terms of your question
so part part of
of the question between us and other Christian groups of this regard.
Our Old Testament is actually a little different
than the Roman Catholic Old Testament.
We actually have a couple more books that they do
if you're Greek and if you're from a Slavic tradition,
we actually have even a couple more than that.
And so it's not an issue really
of those books having been taken out.
The reality is in the early church,
Different
Christian communities in different parts of the world
received an Old Testament that was based on
what the Jewish communities were using in that part of the world.
So in Greek-speaking communities, they received a Greek Old Testament that had books in it
that were not necessarily part of the Hebrew Old Testament,
or of the old test with those being used by
Ethiopian Jews, or Alexandrian Jews, right?
So there were different sort of Old Testaments
that were received.
And so in the West, in Europe, and in the Western part
of North Africa, there were some churches
that only used the Hebrew canon,
which is what Protestants used today,
the Old Testament that most Protestant groups used today.
There were other Latin-speaking churches
The
used the larger Old Testament canon that the Roman Catholic Church uses today and that
the Roman Catholic Church only made that their official Old Testament canon in the 16th century
AD. So before that, for close to 1500 years, there were different sides who debated that
in Western Europe. Which one of those two should be used as the Old Testament?
And on that, as well as a whole bunch of other issues,
when the Protestant Reformation happened,
the Roman Catholic Church sort of took one side
and the Protestant churches took mostly the other side,
and adopted those two canons.
Whereas different Orthodox churches
and different what we call oriental Orthodox churches,
sometimes, or non-Caustodonian churches,
they're still using the same canon they've always used,
that have those extra buttons.
So the answer really for why we as Orthodox Christians have the canon we have
Why we have the Old Testament we have is that this is the list of books that we've received
From the earlier generations of our church and we've just been using it continually all this time
There was never really a big debate or discussion about it in the East
Like what happened in the West
So I hope that helps
Does that does that answer your question Ezra?
Yeah.
So I haven't always a doc study, but I will
my readers books a lot and I like them.
And I just I was just kind of upset that they were taking out.
I guess.
Well, maybe you can share them with your friends if they're open to that.
Yeah, I mean, that's one of the most,
most like most of our Protestant friends are totally unfamiliar
with what's even in those books.
Yeah, and they're really great stories.
stories. Like, Tobit, especially, is such a great story.
So, and you know, bigger Daniel has a dragon. So...
Anyway, all right. Well, thank you very much for calling Andy and Ezra. We're gonna go ahead and take a short break and we will be way better than Ezra.
Way better. Way better. So it will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymek and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hey there, Ancient Faith Radio listeners.
I'm Bobby Maddox, Station Manager of AFR.
And as you might be aware, the very popular Ancient Faith Radio app was canceled unexpectedly
by the company that built and supported.
We apologize for any inconvenience that this may have caused.
news is that we have created a brand new app that will launch this coming
September. Boy will you be pleased with the change. Not only is the interface more
intuitive and easy to use, but the new app will totally revolutionize the way
that you listen to ancient faith radio. Among other features, it will include
the ability to create playlists and share them. And a subscription option that
will keep you up to date on new episodes of your favorite podcasts.
And speaking of favorites, the Apple likewise allow you to mark your profile.
and store them in a convenient accessible location.
We are thrilled with how the new app is turning out
and can't wait to offer it to you.
So fear not, AFR listeners and thanks for your patience.
The new, incredibly robust ancient Faith Radio app
is on its way this coming September.
Look for it soon in your preferred application store.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steve B.
and father Steve.
to young. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back, Dragon Slayer's. So, I mean, I love that ad from Bobby. He always
sounds so positive in those ads. You know, I kept thinking it was me that was going to
It turned out it was the...
It's true!
Yeah, just so.
Literally!
I give you pull it up if you pull it up it says app has been canceled total
Swarth completely true. Yeah, right right so well, I mean, you know, I do want to play though. So there there is an ad that you know
I was I occasionally I get asked to do voice overs promo voice overs and stuff you know
Because I am an agent faith employee and I just wanted to play an ad for your second book father Stephen, you know
So this is one of my favorite ads that I was ever asked to do.
and it's been a long time since any of us have heard this.
So let's go ahead and finally an ad that wasn't a snoozer.
Here we go.
No.
In a world of infanticide, holy war and divine wrath,
Violence may all test him in his long and stumbling block for Christians and skeptics alike.
Yet conventional efforts to understand this violence,
whether by downplaying it as allegory or a relic of primitive cultures,
or by dismissing the authority of scripture altogether,
tend to raise more questions than they answer.
God is a man of war, offers a fresh interpretation of old testimony counts of violence,
by exploring them for the...
full lens of Orthodox tradition and historical context.
Father Steven DeYoung examines what's these difficult passages
reveal about the nature of Christ and his creation.
Very witness to world field not only with pain and suffering,
often of human making, but also with the love of God.
Yeah, you got to love that dramatic background music right there,
right?
Yeah, probably.
sold 10 copies just now. Yeah, and
unfortunately, you know, people
couldn't see the visuals that
went with that, right? The fire,
the explosions, the, you know, the
dancers. Yeah. Yeah. It's true.
All right. Well, we're going to go
ahead and take another call so we've
got Celeste calling and her phone
is from Nevada. So Celeste,
welcome, Florida Spears podcast.
Hi. Okay. You can hear me? Yes,
we hear you. Welcome.
So I'm picking back. I'm going to
Thank you, Dr.
question on Jim's question from earlier in the show. So you said that Adam wasn't
perfect but innocent and mutable but I remember from all your shows you explained
that free will is explained like it's the free will to choose evil is a defect on
that it was a repercussion of the fall.
So how can Adam and Eve do?
to form before they were found.
Yeah, I remember this taking up about three whole sessions
in my seminary classes with our Patristics professor.
And I remember him saying,
this is just my punt to Father Stephen,
but I wanted to add in something.
I remember him saying with his amazing London Cypriot accent
that he had, it was exceedingly difficult.
for them to sin.
So, yeah, I mean, I think, so the one thing I would say is,
the, the, what is really the result of the fall is our
tendency to sin, our tendency to sin, like that we,
we lean in that direction, right?
That's easier to do that.
Not that it's, you know,
the ability to fall only comes because of the fall
right? That doesn't make sense, does it? Right? So that's what I'll add and I'll
I'll pass the puck over to Father Stephen. Yeah, so yeah, so you're basically what
your service is distinction, what it gets called the distinction between the
natural will and what's called the nomencl. There you go. The nomencl being the
sort of second movement of the will that emerges after the fall. And so
that the natural will is really sort of a force that propels us in the direction of our nature.
But, so this is part though of a whole understanding of human choice that really comes out of Aristotle.
I think it's picked up by the fathers. And so it's worth noting that when it comes to
to Fronise's, which is sort of ethical decision making.
Aristotle. He's going to argue there and I think this is implied in the concept of the natural will,
that everyone always chooses the good. And that at first doesn't make any sense to us, right?
Because we're like, well, obviously no. People choose to do evil all the time. Right?
But the point he's trying to make is that people do what they do.
because what they are doing appears good to them at the time.
Yeah.
And we see this in Genesis 3, right?
It talks about how Eve looked at the fruit.
It saw that it was pleasing to the eye, right?
That is all of these, right?
So to her, it appears good, right?
To her it appears good, and that then spurs her action, right?
So we did...
to think of the will purely in that nomic sense of I choose X or I choose Y, I choose A or
I choose not A. But the natural will is this force impelling us toward the good. So the reason
Adam and Eve were able to sin is related to that fact that they were innocent and immature,
right that they had not their their news right there a bill.
to perceive what is truly good was undeveloped and therefore able to be
mistaken, able to be fallible. This is why God forbade them to eat from that tree
in the first place, right? Second-templed Jewish tradition all the way through
the church fathers is that there was nothing evil about the tree per se, but that
Adam and Eve were not ready at that point to receive that wisdom. They were
not yet mature enough.
to receive it. And so God's command was protecting the front. Right. And from the consequences of them eating it, eating it too soon.
So this is part of why, part of what we were talking about the answer to that previous question, why once we have reached that point of maturity in Christ, we will not be capable of sitting again,
Because then through the process of theosis through the
process of our salvation and glorification, our news is purified so that we can correctly
see what is good, what is pure, where God is, right, and we will be able to do that correctly
and infallibly so that we won't need to, right, the the nobic will, that second move will
emerge as after the fall because we need it after the fall, because after the fall our
news is even worse off.
Right so it goes from being a lens that isn't focused properly to being a lens that's cracked and covered in mud
Right and we're still using that lens to try to perceive what is good and what we should do and so
This second movement of the Will emerges to help us in our as a faculty of our indecision
And our inability to clearly discern at all, right, so we're in a worse off state
right, so
all it's been
Dr. Venny was right. It was more difficult for them, right? Because they had greater
access than we do, but their ability to receive the good was not perfect either because
of their immatureness.
Does that make sense to us?
It's a lot to chew on, so I'll just keep it for a while.
Yeah, yeah. We like to do that.
Thank you.
You're welcome. You're welcome.
All right, well, we've got to take another call.
Is this an all Q and A episode?
So we've got our old friend Samuel from Virginia.
Samuel, are you there?
I'm there, fathers.
Welcome back, Samuel, to the Lord of Spheres podcast.
What is on your mind?
Well, I was wondering how much people's understanding
of who and what God is affects how we design our places
to the worship, we both know.
what a church looks like and to contrast with that a few months ago I toured and the nearby
Mormon temple when it was open to the public during their renovations and it did not look like
what I expected church to look like. Honestly, it looked more like a hotel than a church.
But how much of that is from a different understanding of who and what God is
brother then
from something else going on.
That's a great question.
So, you know, like Mormon temples are actually a great example of this, because the concept
of who exactly God is and what it means to be His children and what heaven is like,
this kind of thing, right? This all is expressed in their architecture.
It's all expressed in their architecture.
The reason why, you know, and I agree, I mean, I think that a lot of their rooms do look like a hotel.
And that comes out of this conception of what, you know, the celestial kingdom is like and all this kind of thing.
Whereas traditional Orthodox church architecture comes out of a concept of I mean if you look
Get for instance an eye
kind of all saints and then you look at the inside of an Orthodox church, you're basically seeing the
same thing, right? Christ and thrown at the center, surrounded by, you know, directly next to him,
his mother and John the forerunner and the angels and all the saints. I mean, that's exactly what it is.
An icon of all saints and an Orthodox church are depicting the same thing. The difference between
them is that a church is a ritual space you can actually do things in, right? So, so yes, absolutely,
your concept of who God is, what
It means to meet with him, what it means to be, to dwell with him especially, does affect
your worship space.
I mean, I recall when I was, you know, 25 plus years ago, when I was still in evangelical,
my last stop in the evangelical world was in the beginnings of Omega Church.
And the church, the inside literally was a theater.
Like it just exactly was a theater, you know?
The seating was theater seating.
The stage was a theater stage.
The lighting was seer lighting.
sound the whole thing right and I recall you know discussions about what will
heaven be like were in these exact terms that is going to be sort of a long you
know worship music session right and in that term so so yes absolutely you know
your concept of who God is and what it means to dwell with him is going to be
expressed in your architecture. Father Stephen anything to add or adjust there
Yeah, I mean, with everything like that,
form follows function, right?
So the bridge of Kirk's enterprise
looks like the bridge of a starship
and the bridge of the cards enterprise
looks like a Hilton lobby
where they're having some kind of meeting
to shrimp and talk about diplomatic issues or something.
But, and quote Shakespeare, hello.
Well, yeah.
So, but the same is true with Kirk.
right? If what you're doing is you're going there to see a
presentation then your church is going to look like a theater. Right? If what
you're doing is you're gathering to hear a sermon, everything's going to be
able to lectern up front. And of course, the Orthodox church ultimately are
our churches are patterned after the tabernacle,
which is patterned after...
what Moses saw a top Mount Sinai.
And so it's patterned after the cosmos.
It's patterned after the heavens of the earth.
And we have the altar at the front,
which is the footstool of Christ's throne,
because Christ isn't thrown at the high place.
And we're there to meet with Him and worship Him.
Right?
And that's primarily done through sacrifice.
That's why we have the altar there at the front.
So yeah, very much you're gonna...
design your worship space around what you're intending to do there.
And so it's revelatory of what it is that people think they're doing.
And what they intend to do.
Yeah. Yeah.
Does that answer your question, Samuel?
Yeah, that was very helpful. Thank you.
Awesome. Awesome. Great.
Well, this is our second anniversary episode,
and we're playing some selections of moments from some of our previous favorites.
So I'm going to go ahead and play
another happy memory right now.
So yeah, I mean, there's a lot of UFO abduction stories out there, but I think that one in the clip that we just played.
I think that's the one that I think really needs a response and really needs an explanation.
you know, before before we get to that though, like I just wanted to say that when I
I was in seminary, and of course, you and I both went to the same seminary as St.
Tekons.
I lived in a little town called Simpson, which apparently is actually renowned for being
the site of the first, either Simpson or the town next door, the first car accident in
America.
But Carbondale, Pennsylvania, which is right next to there, and which we used to, amusingly
refer to as Carbondale, because of course, apparently Carbondale, and you can look this
up on the internet people. Carbon Dale is the site of a
a UFO downing, like in a reservoir or something there.
And, you know, I mean, who knows if it was covered
up by the government?
I have no idea.
But I just wanted to point that out.
Right, right.
Yeah.
But so, I mean, a lot of those stories,
I'm not super familiar with the Carbondale story.
But a lot of the stories, you see the same sort
of derivative elements from previous stories, right?
Yeah.
And so it's hard to sort of sort those out.
But in that clip, we just...
I mean, the connections to like, for example, Humbaba in the Epic of Gilgamesh.
Or even some of the stories regarding the God Enke.
They're just so clear.
And this would be the one place where maybe somebody like Zacharias Hitchin or the
documentaries on Fypertv where they might maybe have a point about the whole connection
between this section.
literature and the modern experience of alien abduction and as we just heard cattle medilation.
Right.
And you know, one of the things that fascinated me the most about that recording was how
you can actually connect that with passages from the ancient world with stuff in Scripture
and actually figure out the precise age of the earth, including such events as when the
Exodus happened.
Right.
it all maps out if you just
just track those appearances.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
That to me was one of the most mind blowing episodes ever.
And we had all those people requesting the UFO episode
and we were resisted to doing the UFO episode,
but I'm glad we finally did it.
Yeah, exactly.
When we did.
All right, well, we have another caller we're going to take.
And Michael is calling.
So Michael, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What is up?
on your mind.
Thank you, your father's wife.
God bless you.
I just wanna say I really appreciate your show.
It this and the whole council
and the orthodoxy and heterodoxy
were major stepping stools in my family
and I converting into orthodoxy.
So we really appreciate all the work that you guys have done.
Thank God.
So my question is involves most high God.
So I love to see that.
on a little bit of that.
The whole question now, it's when is the most high God that they're referring to in these texts no longer Yahweh the God of Israel?
I'm looking in particular, I got a copy of the papyrus that Arnie is like with the Egyptian book of the dead.
And in there it starts with praising, in this case it's raw, we're supposed to be the most high and it talks about him.
creating all the other gods and being the other things. But then if you look at that and then you look at
you know other other things like with the golden calves or something like that when the ones that
Aaron put up or the ones that you see the put up in the divided kingdom in northern Israel
verses like in modern Islam where they God is...
as we are just, they say that they understand him better
or even to like Mormons or Jehovah's Witnesses
or all of that.
It seems like everybody in these cases is like saying,
they're talking about the same person,
but at what point are they no longer actually
talking about the same person?
Hmm, I think I see what you're saying.
So like, I mean, this seems to be a permutation
of the question of, you know, is the God
that Muslims and Jews and Christians worship
truly the same God, right?
Is that...
to kind of what you're talking about.
Right, and like was was the Yahweh of the Golden Caves
actually Yahweh the God of Israel just being worshiped
incorrectly is is is raw in this case actually Yahweh the God
of Israel just with a different name and bad understanding
like where's the line between okay, you're still worshiping
the actual most high versus no now there's an air looper.
Yeah, yeah, so I mean the place that I
would start would be to say that, you know, if someone is teaching heresy, like, right,
for instance, let's say someone says that God is, you know, unitarian monotheistic God,
God is only one person, right? That of course does not change who God is. My God is still
God. He's still Father, Son and Holy Spirit. That's just an eternal reality, right? So,
So the fact of heresy does not change you got
God is. The question then is when does someone's worship of their mistaken version of God actually
veer away into worshiping something else? I think is that what you're sort of saying?
Right, exactly.
Yeah, okay, okay. I mean, I think, well, number one, if someone is trying to worship
raw and not Yahweh, that's clearly someone else. I mean, the depiction of who raw is is
quite different, you know? Or as of course Father Stephen reminded, it's actually pronounced
But I never get rid of that way, at least in English.
And then where it gets sticky is when you're talking about like heretical versions of Christianity,
like unitarianism, for instance, as a good example of this.
And I would say that inasmuch as someone is trying to worship the One through God,
God even doing it imperfectly.
in as much as they are being faithful to what he said, they are doing that. But of course,
it's mixed with other stuff and that other stuff can be a problem. Now, if they're doing that out
of ignorance, I believe that God is going to be merciful to their ignorance. Right? That he's not
going to say, well, you got it wrong. If you'd only moved, you know, flipped your doctrine 0.5 degrees
north, you would have been fine, right? That's not to say that doctrine doesn't matter. But I think
that int-
does matter. You know, if someone is is trying to worship Yahweh, the God of Israel, the Father,
Son and Holy Spirit, but doing it badly, that's better than someone who knows better and chooses
something else, right? So, so I don't know if there's a precise line that you can identify,
I clearly you can see that someone trying to worship Zeus if they do.
it's Zeus clearly is a different figure than Yahweh, right?
If he's embedded within the whole matrix of Greek myth,
it's clear that this is a different being, right?
But then of course you have the scenario like,
you know what you see in, I think it's the last battle in
C.S. Lewis's Narnian Chronicles where you've got someone who's worshipping
this false god in the book who's called Tash.
And
yet the way that they're worshiping, Tash somehow is him actually worshiping
Aslan who is the line who is the Jesus figure in there.
You know, so this idea of kind of the noble pagan on some level, right?
The pagan who's trying to worship the one true God but doesn't know that
that's what he's doing, right? He's sort of being accidentally faithful or
or ignorantly faithful really is kind of the thing. So I don't know that there's
like a clear line. I know I already said that but I but that's my
Conclusion.
on that. I don't know, Father Stephen, you want to add adjust correct, whatever.
Well, I think there's two different things here. Okay. So the first one is, right, most
high God is a title, right? L.O. Yone, right? It's a title. And so yeah, for Egyptians,
raise the most high god for uh bail worshippers L later bail is
the most high god for Greek pagans Zeus is the most high god and for Israelites Yahweh is the most
high god right. The fact that they all apply that same title does not imply in any way that they're
the same being it's they have a disagreement over who that title rightly belongs to right
because most high God is sort of like you know
lit being the best power pop band of the late. Right? You might be wrong and
disagree. Right? But if you say, no, man, bowling for soup is the greatest
power pop band of the late 90s or early 2000s, then we're not talking about the
same band. We're disagreeing about who that title belongs to. Right? And you see
that like in the new testament the new
Intestimate uses Otheos, the articular form, right?
The God is how it's sometimes put in English
to refer to the Father.
Whereas if you read classical literature,
Otheos is Zeus.
Right, again, that's not an argument
that they're the same person.
It's who does that title,
sort of God with a capital G really, really belong to?
Now the other piece, that's the first piece,
but the second piece, right?
is in terms of sort of father Andrew was brushing a little too close to the anonymous Christian's
idea for me. But he was CS Lewis to get up a little bit. But so the question is, you know,
are these other groups? We're going to say, God, to me, the question there is a question about
knowledge. Right, level of the knowledge of God.
God, what level of the knowledge of the true God is required in order to worship and follow
the true God?
Truthfully, right?
And it's a good thing that perfect knowledge is it required or we'd all be in bad trouble,
right?
And I don't just mean that rhetorically, right?
Even from our perspective as people who may have done a bunch of reading of the church
fathers in studying the doctor of the trinity. If we gave an essay.
exam to orthodox Christians, good, faithful orthodox Christians and ask them in an essay to explain
the doctor to the Trinity. We'd be mostly heretics, right? We would get something wrong at bare minimum.
If we didn't have a whole wrong headed conception, we'd have something or some turn of phrase or
some preposition we use that was technically a heresy, right? That doesn't mean that because we
You don't.
have that knowledge, we don't have that higher level of understanding that we're not really worshiping
the true God. We're not really Orthodox Christians, right? It's that our knowledge is imperfect.
And so God accepts imperfect knowledge. But what we find over and over again, for example,
the scriptures is that when someone is worshiping the true God with an imperfect knowledge,
They have more knowledge given to them.
So exhibit A would be like Cornelius.
the centurion, right?
As far as we know Cornelius was still technically a pagan,
the fact that he was still a centurion in the Roman legions
means he was participating in pagan sacrifices
on a fairly regular basis.
But it is heart he had a love for and wanted to follow
the God of Israel.
And so he was giving all, he was making donations
to the Jewish temple.
He was praying.
Seems like probably in his own prayers, at least,
to the God of Israel.
And so because he's doing that, the angel comes to him and says,
Hey, you know, your prayers and your alms have gone up,
like incense, right?
Is it offering before the Lord?
And so we're now sending someone to you and say Peter gets sent to him
to teach him the gospel, right, to raise his level of knowledge
so that he can more truthfully worship the true God.
So I have no doubt
that there are people out there who are endeavoring to worship the true God, to worship and follow
Jesus Christ as best they know how. Like those Christians I was talking about earlier who aren't
necessarily the Orthodox Church. Those people are out there. And there may be some of them who,
you know, because they grew up in a Muslim country or something, you know, don't have even any
Christian words to apply to it, right? But you could go and go
Google this, there's been a rash over the last couple of decades of Muslims and Muslim countries
having visions of Christ, visions of the Thayotokos, that are not all that dissimilar from what
happened with Cornelius.
So this is a thing that happens.
And so those people, God reaches out to them and raises their level of knowledge when someone
is doing that in truth.
That's of course offered to all of us because none of us.
as I said, none of our knowledge is perfect.
And so all of us need to continue to seek wisdom
in the knowledge of God and to grow in our faith.
Because none of us have sort of arrived and got,
I've got who God is down pat now.
I've got that all worked out.
Like that's the surest sign that you're believing
a heresy that there is, that you think you have it all
worked out.
So I hope those between those two things
that kind of answers your question.
It does, it does, that's very helpful.
I have one quick question on a totally different topic
if I'm A. All right.
The, so Dungeons and Dragons.
Okay.
Is it possible to share the gospel and convert orcs
and goblins and dragons and cobalt and all those kinds
of things like, are they image barriers to the degree
that they can be converted?
Well, within Dungeons and Dragons.
new. Within the real world, new. Because a monster is a monster. You know, that's what
monsters are in stories is their monsters. Well, but within judges of dragons, you could
craft a world. You could do your home brew campaign world. I guess it's such a way that
that were possible. I mean, you could cast charm on all of them. I suppose and like keep
casting it forever. I'm saying you could you
it to hey, they've done the Bible is a setting for fifth edition. Yeah. Let's not go there.
But I know. But anyway, everyone's going to scrambling now to look that up now. Yes.
Yes. Find it. It's in there. But yeah, I mean, here's what I'll say to take your question
a little bit more seriously, Michael, although I don't know how seriously you meant it.
to take a little bit more seriously.
I've spent a lot of time actually working on this question of dragons.
And I mean, what is a dragon?
Within a story, a dragon is, by definition, a demonic force that is there to prove the
hero.
So it's like saying, can I preach the gospel and convert demons?
The way that demons actually function within the Christian mythos is that they're the
enemies of God.
Like that's our only actual experience of them.
how they're always depicted within the...
story, right? So I mean, can I imagine some other thing happening? Yeah, I can imagine it. But
that doesn't mean that that works according to, you know, what my favorite author would call
the Canon of Canon's of narrative art, right? Like he would, you know, I'm referring to Tolkien,
of course, but I mean, he would hate like the modern depictions of dragons as being like
people's pets and friends and stuff, because he would say that's not according to the
Canon's of narrative art. And it's not because he's some kind of hardliner about how you tell
stories, it's just...
that there is there's a reason why this tradition of what a dragon is functions the way that it always
has within legends and tales and stuff. Right. So that's why I said what is a monster? Well, a monster
is a monster. You know, like if you read Beowulf, are you supposed to feel bad for Grendel? I mean,
you might want to, but the Beowulf poet certainly doesn't. He's a monster. That's what is
function of the story is so I don't know if that helps at all Michael but I object I'll drag
are not chromatic. Okay. The talus dragons are seraphim. Okay, I will, yes, I will grant you that.
I will grant you that. Yes, I will, I will grant you that. Yeah. Yeah. So anyway.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling Michael. All right. We're going to take
Alexandra next. So Alexandra, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
to have it be here.
Yeah, you made it through.
Yeah, I did.
Okay, awesome.
So my question is, in the story of Christ
hearing the parliotic at the pool,
we seem to get the lesson that the healing
comes not in the water but from Christ.
We also see that it's up to be an angel
that is stirring up the water.
And actually I noticed I was saying visual
for the Sunday of the parliotic
and we had the refrain like we're in a holy resurrection
of Laura but there's also one step to the Arfangil Michael.
So how are we to understand this angelic work
Thank you.
being put almost in opposition to the work of Christ.
Or is that not the way to understand it?
Well, I mean, no angelic work is in opposition to Christ.
That's not possible.
Angels obey Him and everything they do,
they're basically sent on that mission by it.
So I don't know, Father, I mean, what do you think
in this regard?
I mean, yeah.
So, on the other hand.
nerd out moment. Oh yeah. There's a huge question about that little bit in
in St. John's text about the angel coming down and troubling the water. Because
if there's there are weird textual variants there like which texts it's in and
which text it isn't in follows like none of the normal patterns for
textual variants in the New Testament. Like it's in older text and not more
recent text. It's in.
that are normally considered to be non-expansionist,
meaning that don't normally have added things in them.
And it's not in texts that do tend to have added things in them.
So it's an interesting little thing there.
Crucks, as it were.
Yeah.
And I won't bore you with it, but I was once part of it.
And a PhD seminar, like a half hour debate
about that couple of verses.
Right.
Because that's what you do when you work on a PhD you
argue about minutiae for extended
Papers have to be written
But so part of this is
This story and a number of other stories similarly in the Gospels
show us that
There's sort of a normal order of things within the created order and then there is Christ, right?
So, for example, and we just read this text on Sunday a few weeks ago,
there's a text where the disciples try to cast the demon out of the boy and they can't.
And Christ walks up and just casts the demon out of this,
and this kind of only comes through prayer and fasting.
What we don't read about Christ doing any praying or fasting.
Right?
Good.
He didn't have to.
Right.
He wasn't saying like, this is the only technique
by which you could drive out this.
You say, for you, this is what you're gonna need to do.
Right.
And we see something similar with the paralytic
in that, right, the paralytic from his perspective,
when Christ interacts with him,
says, well, the reason I haven't been healed
is that when the angel comes and troubles the waters,
somebody else jumps in first.
That's why I have-
it been healed, right? And Christ doesn't then wait for the angel to come and then throw him in the water.
Right. Christ just heals him because he's God. He could do that, right? And so we tend to, right,
when I started this, I said, there's an order of creation and then there's there's exception to it.
most of us modern people hearing that when we hear there's an order to
creation, we think, oh, yes, scientific laws. And then sometimes
miracles happen. Right. And that's not the paradigm of scripture.
The paradigm of scripture is there's a way that creation works.
And that includes the visible and invisible creation. That includes
the material creation, that includes spirits like angels and demons.
Right. All of that is included. And then there are also times where
God.
acts directly without any intermediary.
So all of the healings are God's doing.
Sometimes he does it through intermediaries.
Sometimes he does it through an angel.
Sometimes he does it through a doctor or a surgeon.
Sometimes he just does it directly.
And we as humans distinguish between,
we say the times within intermediaries,
those are quote unquote natural.
In fact, we might not-
even give God all of the credit, unfortunately, right? Because of the intermediary. And then we say
the others are exceptions. But really, those are all sort of of a piece. It's just a question of
God not being bound by the intermediaries. Yeah. Right. Christ could heal through that angel and the pool
or he could do it directly. Right. Yeah. I recall, um, I think it's in one of his homelies.
St. Nick Lave.
I might have references on the show before I don't know.
But in one of his homelies, he talks about this question of what is a miracle.
And he says, miracles are simply gifts from God at which men marvel.
The point being that everything that is good comes from God.
That every, like there is no good apart from God.
from God. There's no other source of good.
the giver of all good things. But there's some of those gifts at which we go, whoa, and
that's the stuff that we call a miracle. But really, it's still from him. So it doesn't
– I know sometimes people, for instance, when they refer, they look at a baby being
born or something like this, they'll say, oh, that's the miracle of birth. And then
someone will say, no, that's not a miracle. That's just normal. That's natural, whatever.
The f***
fact that there's this kind of discrepancy between the way people refer to it, even if it's not
really true, truly two different ways of thinking about it, like the people who say, you know,
birth is a miracle are not saying something supernatural just happened in front of me.
Right? But the fact that there is discrepancy is kind of getting at this reality that on some level
everything is a miracle, but really I think it's better just to see everything as a gift from God.
And I like what
what St. Nicholas says, miracles are just gifts from God at which we marvel.
But sometimes we marvel at things that other people might not regard as being, quote, unquote,
supernatural.
Right?
That, you know, I mean, in the years that I served as a pastor, and even now, when I see,
when I see someone who is hardened in a way of thinking or behaving truly convert, that
is marvelous to me because I don't know.
I mean serving as a priest is pretty easy to get kind of
cynical because it's not a lot of conversion that's really happening in front of you, you know.
So it is pretty marvelous and it feels miraculous to me when I see that kind of thing, even though it's
not what most people would think of as supernatural. But I mean, all good things come from God.
All good things come from God. And I think one of the best things that we can do is Christians is to
to apply that in a truly pervasive way.
And then when we do that, then we find ourselves, as the scripture says, in everything giving thanks
because everything is given to us from him.
Right? So, you know, whether it's an angel stirring up water and healing happening when someone connects to that or it's just, or it's Jesus walking up and saying, get up.
The giver is the same giver in both cases. Right?
Well.
Does that make sense, Alexander?
Yes, thank you. And I have to say as someone who's currently pregnant for the first time,
the baby annalty is particularly apt. Thank you very much.
All right. I mean, although I'll say this, right, like, you know, a baby being born does
not seem like a supernatural thing. But when you conceive for a moment, pun fully intended
that there was not this human. And now there is this human. I don't know how that works.
I mean, I know how it works biologically, but like, but this is a person it's not.
You know, it's not just a phenomenon.
That's really interesting to me.
I have four kids and I think about the fact
that they used to not exist.
I don't know.
You know, that's the point where my wife
and I look at each other and go,
I don't know what we ever did without him or without her.
How could there ever been a world without you?
You know, that's the unexplainable thing
at which we marvel.
You know, so congratulations on your pregnancy.
It's such an amazing...
occasion to be a mom. So God be with you in that.
Thank you, Pastor.
All right. Well, thank you very much for that.
We're going to go ahead and take our second break.
And we will be right back on this all Q&A episode of The Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment.
To take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits,
give them a call at 855-237-2346.
Let's eat five.
5-8-S radio.
Hi, this is Jerry Minneto, so I'm the development director here at Ancient Faith Ministries.
As you might already know, part of my responsibilities as a development director is to reach out to
what are called major donors and share with them the reach and influence of Ancient Faith
Radio.
Of course, I do that and occasionally this results in a fairly large financial gift, maybe
aim to the specific AFR.
our project or towards our general operations.
Glory be to God and thank you when this occurs.
However, I'll share with you a secret.
Here at Ancient Faith, we consider every donor
a major donor.
I wish that I could and I do try
to reach out to as many of you as I can.
And practically speaking, relying on a handful
of Apple and individuals or institutions
for the bulk of your revenue is not a good recipe.
Using one or two of these supporters
and you're suddenly in trouble
when it comes to keeping the ministry of
We've never done that here at Ancient Faith.
We've relied on you.
Our wonderful listeners who give 10, 20, 50, $100 on a monthly or one-time basis.
Glory be to God.
Fortunately, this is the model that Ancient Faith Radio has always utilized and will continue
to do.
Reach out to you.
It's one of the reasons that we choose at the station to be entirely listener supportive.
Would you please consider joining the many who have already committed to sustaining IFA
with the modest monetary gift.
We say modest, but everything is appreciated.
Every little bit does so much to keep the lights on and the audio rolling.
Be a participant, be a partner.
Support Ancient Faith Radio today by clicking on Donate in the upper right hand corner
of Ancient Faith.com.
Thank you in advance for your generosity.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
to young. If you have a question call now at 855
237 2346. That's 855 AF radio.
All right. Thank you, voice of Steve. Yeah.
Let me go. Okay. Let me just say. Yeah. Let me just say,
if anybody's considering a major monetary gift to a particular AFR
podcaster, I could give you my PayPal.
I've got, I've got student loans, man.
Can't you just get another PhD and defer those loans for another
in January.
or something. I'm already doing that. But yeah, everybody give us a call. It's an all Q&A episode.
That's all we're doing tonight. So if you don't call us, we're just going to go ahead and go to bed
or whatever it is that Father Stephen does after he hangs up. To that end though, we're playing
some of our favorite clips from big memories from the past. And I've got one more I wanted to share.
So here it is, let's play that way back machine.
So we're going to go ahead and take a call. And according to my call board here, we have Steve calling from Staten Island. So Steve, welcome to Lord of Spears podcast. Are you there? Can you hear me?
I am here. You can hear me okay? Yeah, yeah, welcome welcome to the podcast so
What's on your mind? Yeah, well thanks for taking my call
Though this might be more of a rambling comment the question, but I'd love to hear your
actions as I try to connect some dots that I've been thinking about for a while.
At least from Father Stephen, who is super based, Father Andrew on the other hand is a soy
boy, at least according to the orthodox apologists that I follow online who are all very stable
geniuses and doing wonderful things with church.
So anyway, I want to thank you for the show because it got me to a couple of things which
got me into Joe Rogan, which got me into Alex Jones, and it's all open by eye to something
that's been staring me in a face for a long, long time because I feel like all these elite
The secret to silence.
the 80s, skull and bones, builder burger, the Illuminati, it's finally clicked, right?
But they're all neighborhood.
And I'm glad that you guys had the courage to expose this because it's really been something
that's been haunting us for so long.
I'm thinking about this, right?
Everything from Comic-Ping Pong and Epstein's Island, places where pedophilic corporate elites
are engaged in weird sexual rituals to produce new generations of nephilim that rise through
the ranks of the deep states and are currently trying to destroy our one true president.
And the more that I think, as I learned about Hollywood occultism,
a liberal agenda to host drag shows in every kindergarten across the country.
The more proud I am to be a base and red-filled Orthodox Christians,
and I wouldn't have been awakened to any of this without this.
So sorry, that was more of a comment in a question.
That's been a lot of stuff that are on my mind.
I'll take my response off the air.
Well, you know, I mean, this is what our whole previous episode was completely about.
So, I mean, yeah, you've heard us.
I think it's time that people understand all this.
I don't know if I thought of Stephen, you have any comments on this and you're on the
actualy's?
Well, I mean...
I think sometimes because of the way we talk about things, right, we're talking about the
spiritual world, we're trying to tell people not to be materialists, that they sometimes
take it too far in the other direction, right.
And maybe they don't understand sort of the direct application to our day-to-day lives,
like what our call just laid out.
Yeah, right.
And I mean, if you don't understand all.
that I don't know how you make just your day to day decisions, right, about how to live
your life as a Christian, making basic moral choices without that grit, right, that he
just described. Yeah, exactly. Well, good for you. You get it, Caller. Thanks very much
for calling in, Steve.
That warmed my heart right there. One of my favorite calls ever. As much as I enjoyed
that call, you know.
We've replayed it now and he was kind of saying the quiet part out loud.
You know, yeah, like it's a little too on the nose.
Maybe we shouldn't have played that one.
The reveal is a little like.
I do have to say though, I know you like to follow the fast really strictly and that kind
of restricts your food options.
You could lay off the soy.
A little bit.
I will keep that in mind.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'll see you next time.
a while since we had tofu. So I feel like I'm making some progress here. That's good.
Yeah, since that episode, at least. Yeah. And I've never been into edamame. That's
soy, right? I don't know. I don't eat that kind of stuff anyway. All right. We're going
to go ahead, take some more calls. So we've got Yvonne calling. Yvonne, welcome to the Lord
of Spirits podcast. What is on your mind? Yeah. Hi. Thank you for taking my call. Can
Can you hear me?
Yes, we hear you. Welcome.
All right, okay, thank you, Father's.
Okay, so this is going back to earlier in the show
when you were talking about Adam and Eve.
I just kind of wanted you to expand on that a little bit.
Like, it sounded like you were saying that,
that they showed poor judgment
and that they were immature
and that Eve, you know, she saw this thing is good, right?
So, and I have this had this question for a while in my head
and I also, I don't want to be guilty of like,
full of teaching to my children
because the way I've explained it.
might be incorrect, but was she being self-righteous
or were they both being self-righteous
in that they were using their own bodies
to take this whatever it was, right?
And to take it into herself and to say,
oh, it looks good, it tastes good,
it's good, like, you know, their immature,
they're like children, right?
They're using their bodies,
because the comparison that I have always given to my kids
for a while, which could be wrong, I hope it's not,
Okay.
that like if a two year old was in their bedroom, say, right, and the
hero bird and it's pleasing to the child's body, right? Like, oh, my
year drum sound great, you know? It would be proper for the child
because the bird's not bad, right? But it would be proper for the
child to say, mom, dad, look at the bird, which should be my
next step, rather than to just say, oh, it sounds good and jump
out the window. You know what I mean? I'm flying the birds back
because it's not gonna work.
So was that like an example of self-righteousness,
where she was kind of just, am I off on that?
I'm tracking with you.
I think that that works.
And I think part of, you know, a big piece of the scenario
right is that Adam and Eve did not encounter the fruit,
completely, you know, a new right?
Yeah
God had told them.
Don't you?
You look at it, they could touch it.
Don't eat it.
Yes, yes, he ingested it.
She took it into her body.
But I mean, you know, I'm assuming
she could have disliked it, touched it.
You know what I mean?
And also because there's so much symbolism
when you say the fruit.
Like, fruit could be anything like the fruit of the spirit.
That's not like something you eat.
That's like a product of.
You know what I mean?
So like, yeah, that's fruit used as a metaphor.
Yes, sir.
Yeah, thank you, Ray.
Yeah, yeah, I mean it like I said they have this command from God don't eat it, right?
But yeah, but at the same time of course
Eve was under deception she believed what the serpent told her
Right, he was convincing her to do this thing
Right
What would they have?
Yeah, right
So so is my analogy a bad one?
I mean every
now. You know, you know, she was being self-righteous or to compare her to self-righteousness or to say that
if a person is being self-righteous, will they're being silly like how Eve was? Like, is that a bad
connection that I'm making? I wouldn't use the word self-righteous because to me that, um,
because right or wrong, like she said, oh, that's the right direction, but it wasn't.
Yeah, I mean that's she's deceived she's deceived
She's wrong about this, right?
But self-righteousness is more a sense of judgmentalism
towards other people.
And that's not really in the scenario at all.
Yeah, so I don't know.
Father Steven, is there anything you wanted to add
or subtract, multiply the divide?
Quickly, quickly, quickly.
Can I just say this?
Because when you're being self-righteous,
aren't you using yourself rather than God to judge?
Like isn't that what that means?
Sam Lawford.
right? Because I thought that's the self-righteous meant. I don't like if I'm being self-righteous,
I'm saying, well, I don't like that, but maybe God does. You know what I mean? Like, isn't...
It's... that you think you're right because you're you. Right? You know? I'm the one who's
right. You're using... Yeah, so I mean, you're not... If you're off a little, you're not
far off. Right? That a self-righteous person uses their self as the measure of righteousness,
rather than accept.
like for example, God's measure of what righteousness is.
Right.
And so yeah, I don't think your examples are bad.
I mean, you're talking to kids, right?
So I mean, you don't need to get...
They're grown out.
Oh, but I mean, when you're talking to kids,
you don't need to convey every nuance, right?
I was like everything, right?
But you're trying to get a course sort of a main point.
And so I think your example is good in terms of communicating
the idea that it wasn't that
the tree or the fruit was evil, that it wasn't just an arbitrary rule that God made, but God made
this rule to protect them. And he had to make the rule to protect them because they didn't know
for themselves, right? They weren't able to judge that correctly for themselves. The example I usually
use is, you know, you tell a little kid not to go play in the street, right? And to the kid, it may
seem like, well hey, if I run out the street I could run farther.
than if I just run around my yard and they like running.
So it might seem good to them to go run in the street.
But you know that trucks come down the street.
They might not understand that, right?
That they could get hurt doing that, right?
But so I think that's a similar example
to jumping out the window, right?
Right.
Exactly.
You need a boundary.
Right.
That we don't do what seems right in our own eyes, right?
Because in our humility, we accept that I don't always
No
What's good and what's bad for me?
We trust the judgment of someone else. We trust God's judgment ultimately
Right, so if I if I judge somebody, but it's according to the Bible. I'm not really judging them
I'm just applying God's judgment. Well, no because
God God didn't give you the Bible for that purpose
Okay
Yeah, I mean there's a difference between there's a difference between discerning what is right and what is wrong
right?
and maybe being the person, for instance, if you're a parent, right?
Part of your task is to correct your children, to teach your children, right?
But that's a different thing than simply observing someone doing something that is wrong
and deciding that they're damned or unworthy of God's love or whatever in your heart.
You know, that's a different kind of judgment.
If you say, is there a deal? Okay, so then real fast, and this is my last question, I promise.
If I condemn somebody.
in my heart. Is that the same as judging them and also if I say, oh well, let's take for
example homosexuality. Homosexuality is good. Is that also judgment? Like is judgment only
because to me you're judging if you say it's good or it's bad. So the person who says,
well homosexuality is fine is as judgmental as the one who says homosexuality is bad and
is saying, well, it's bad, is that the same thing as?
condemning them because for example when the woman is before the Lord and he says,
if anyone here condemn you and she says no, he says neither do I. That's he saying, I don't condemn you
is condemnation the same thing is saying, well that's bad and that's it that's my last question.
Yeah so there's a difference between
discerning the rightness or wrongness of an action and
a person who's doing something that is wrong. Right? There's a difference between saying it is wrong
to engage in and homosexual acts. That is true. That is simply true. That is not being judgmental.
That's being that's discerning what is right and wrong. But if you say this person who is doing
homosexual acts as damned to hell, that is not within our purview to do. We're not we're not given
in that. Right, absolutely not.
Okay, I understand.
Absolutely not.
All right.
I'm glad that was helpful.
Okay, well thank you very much for calling you on.
And we have Marcus Nex.
So Marcus, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What is on your mind?
Hi, thank you so much for taking my call.
So my question is about the connection
between idolatry and sexual immorality.
Okay.
So I think you mentioned in the past that,
that you know, either very closely related
Alright.
identical, but the way I'm thinking about it is that God is
created, God is Father. So I participate in that by becoming a
father and sexual acts that would lead to that. And when I have
sexual acts that are different than that, then I'm being Zeus, or
I'm being the weird Egyptian God who disturbed himself, which
have or whatever. So yeah, I'm just trying to understand.
What is the exact relation between those two?
And then kind of related to that,
there's all this imagery about sculpting a jealous god,
about the bride and the bridegroom.
And as a red-blooded guy, it just kind of strikes me
as kind of strange.
Like is it saying that god is like the active partner,
and I have to be the passive partner.
Like
it sounds odd to me. I don't understand what I'm supposed to do as that image.
Okay. All right. Well, you know, with regards to the first thing, the thing that really links
idolatry and sexual immorality in particular is that both are about serving oneself.
Right? So the point of idolatry, you know, the way that it works, right, is to control a God
so that the God will do for you what you want.
and sexual immorality is exactly the same, right?
Which is, you know, why there's so many commands about
both of these things, of course, in Scripture and how they're almost always associated together in Scripture.
Right? And, you know, God creates man's capability of worship to be directed towards Him.
He creates man's capability of sexual reproduction to be directed towards reproduction.
reproduction right that is its telos its its purpose
You know, and so there's not necessarily a mechanistic cause causative, you know, causal
relationship between these two things, but they always go together, right?
They always go together.
And you know, we see that again and again in scripture.
And you know, so we've talked about that, of course, many, many times on the show.
I'm not as clear on the second, but before we get to that though, I don't know, Father
or Steven, you want to add anything to that link between idolatry.
and morality. Well there's also the the connection of the body, right? Because of course
idolatry is is the body of a God, right? Or a scene as that, right? That is used to then
manipulate, right? And control the God. And in the same way, of course, our body, especially
if we're Christians, St. Paul makes this point, is the temple of the Holy Spirit, having
Spirit of God dwelling within us.
being members of the body of Christ, that what we do with our body in terms of sexual immorality
is not just sort of a question of moral uncleanness or moral impurity but also of ritual impurity
and sort of sacrilege.
And so that's another way in which in addition to what Father Andrew said, in which those
ideas are.
are sort of united in the scriptures.
In terms of the second part,
the analogy that God uses beginning in the Old Testament
and then it sort of blossoms in the idea of the church
as the bride of Christ in the New Testament
but of Israel and then Israel and Judah
as sort of his bride or his wife.
That's really...
That's culturally steeped, right?
Because of course, when we're talking about our relationship with God, we are definitely
the partner with the least power, right?
In the ancient world of men and women, women had the least societal and social and economic
and every other kind of sort of power to make things happen, right?
So, they women were entirely dependent.
in the ancient world on the men in their lives,
what first their father and then later their husband.
And so this is why widows and orphans
had to be the subject of sort of special protections
because legally in the ancient world
a woman couldn't give testimony in court even.
So if someone wronged her, she couldn't even testify
on her own behalf.
So that put them in this position.
So part of the analysis.
that God is using is that when God first comes to us and offers us his love and
everything that comes with that, everything else he offers to us, we are
essentially powerless, right? These aren't things that we could do for ourselves
if left to our own devices, right? These are gifts that he gives us and in the same
way right that that what he wants again could
continuing the analogy, all he asks for from us in return is our love and our faithfulness.
Right. And so the comparison that's made of the Old Testament prophets is to a wealthy man who
goes and finds some woman in destitution and poverty and marries her and gives her shares
with her everything he has and then she goes and is unfaithfully. Right.
She goes and is disloyal to him.
So it's not so much that we are completely passive
in salvation, sorry Calviness.
But it's that what we do in salvation
is not the providing of the blessings, right?
Of the theosis, right?
This is God's doing.
but we respond with love and with faithfulness.
And love and faithfulness are not emotions.
Right?
Any, any married person, I don't know if you're married,
but any married person can tell you
that love and faithfulness within a marriage
is not primarily about your feelings on any given day.
It's about what you do every day.
And the same is true of our relationship with Christ, right?
And I love it faithfulness is about what we do every...
day. And that those things that we do out of love and faithfulness are our part in working
out our own salvation. So we're not passive, but this isn't a 50 50 split. It's not even
a 90 10 split. I mean, you'd have to go out to a lot of decimal points to represent it
numbers. And even then, yes, it may be a little bit function.
approaching zero, right? Yeah, so does that make sense, Marcus? That makes a loss and you've given me
something to chew on. I'm sure I'll call you again in the future. Thank you for all you do and all
the content you provide. Thank you. Thank you. And thanks for listening. All right, we've got another
call and we've got Nathan calling. So Nathan, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast. Speak.
you
Thank you, fathers.
I just had a quick question, a little confusion
over your previous episode on the Tower of Babel.
When you first talked about it way, way back
in a long, long ago, I thought I understood that the fallen
angels, I was calling the overseers of the nations,
had to do some away for God.
But then when I was listening to the episode,
you're going in detail.
It sounded like...
It was people that was tempting them to set themselves up as false gods and so I was wondering
You know, it was which side was kind of it fault there or was it some sort of like mutual feedback loop of the two groups
Okay, I'm not sure I totally understand the question, but I do all right good
Maybe I can understand about this thing.
So in luck.
In large part, it's a feedback loop.
But St. Denis' theory, Opogite, for example,
make wants to make it very clear that that feedback loop
starts with human instigation.
Okay.
That God did not assign fallen beings
to oversee the nations, or to tempt them,
or to lead the mystery.
But so this is the humans were the motivating factor.
That's all I was missing.
So one quick follow up then,
does this play into or affect the later part
of the New Testament where it is said that we will judge angels
or that just seemed to me as well.
So I mean, yeah, yeah.
But also we should say that judge
is not just a matter of like...
rendering a verdict, like you did a bad thing, you know, it's, you know, as we've said
many times in the show, right, establishing justice. This is what judging is, is putting
things in order, right? So, so, you know, when I go in my backyard and I mow the lawn,
I'm establishing justice. I'm judging the lawn, right? That's, you know, to use that same
language. So so
that judging function of human beings in life of the H2KM is about an ordering function.
Right? So that's also a big piece of what's going on there.
So you're cutting down the grass with the side of torment?
Oh yeah, totally. That's right. Actually, if I use the side...
I'll break out the weed germer.
I'll actually do that.
There you go. I'm... honey, I'm going to go get the weed whacker and execute judgment upon this
the CRT.
Absolutely true. All right. Well, thank you very much for calling Nathan. We have Cameron calling. I think all the way from the Great White North. So Cameron, are you there?
I'm not sure Cameron is connected. Speak to us Cameron. Who did this to you?
Hello, father. Cameron. Yes, we hear you. Welcome to the Lord of Spheres podcast. We're listening.
All right, thanks, others. Well, first of all, thanks for the pie.
of my spiritual father introduced me to orthodoxy and heterodoxy and it's been downhill ever since.
So, I think that's the best way.
Have you hit rock bottom yet?
Hopefully he mostly introduced you to orthodoxy, less to the heterodoxy.
Okay, so I'm going to quick to a part question for you.
What's what happened with Rho in the US?
There's been a lot of talk of abortion over the border too.
person quickly.
I've seen people talking about how the Old Testament didn't necessarily disallow abortion.
And I'm kind of like, you guys have read the Psalms, man.
And I'm saying like, they're assuming that life in the womb isn't the life of the Ten Commandments.
I'm guessing don't necessarily apply in their view.
So I'm curious if your father's knowledge of Old Testament would say to that.
But second and maybe more important, there's something I've been thinking about lately,
is if we have to legislate abortion to stop people from doing it, how we already...
lost. I've been thinking about this a lot while reading Timothy Patissus book about the ethics of
beauty and how we must take a beauty first approach to things beauty first and goodness and truth.
So like you know if we're yelling at people or setting a protest or putting up signs against
abortion really it seems to me like a true first approach and likely why the battles being lost.
I had been up all this effort was put into maybe a beauty first approach. What would that look like?
Hopefully my question makes sense.
I think so.
I mean, there's a bunch of different angles from this to look at this question, right?
And I would say also that there are multiple angles from which to work on it.
And some people are going to be good at some angles and some people are going to be good
at others, right?
Number one, I do believe, I very much do believe that it is right and proper for there to be
you laws.
not to kill people, right? This is something I think it is right for the government to do is to
restrain public evil. Now, I don't think that governments need to pass laws against every
single possible evil, right? I mean, it's evil if someone looks at another person and lusts
and his heart. That's evil, I don't think that should be against the law.
Right, it's, it's, you know, it's evil. It's bad for your soul. It's bad for their soul, right?
But I don't think it needs to be against the law. But, but it is appropriate in Christian tradition,
in the scripture, for governments to restrain public evil doers, right? You know, if someone is
murdering other people, that it's appropriate for the government to stop that. Now, that's not to
say that there isn't
work to be done on building communities and nurturing human beings and addressing poverty
and all this other stuff, right, that we know mitigates these kinds of public acts of
evil if these other things are worked on too, right?
You know, like, for instance, I have four kids and one of the questions, if one of the kids
is acting out, one of the questions that we will often ask is, have you eaten?
a cranky child is often...
a hungry child is often an angry child and an angry child might well be a violent child.
But at the same time if one of the children is beating up on his brother it is absolutely appropriate for
me to go and grab hold of his arms and make him stop doing that. Right? You know now I may then go
lead him to say why don't you have some dinner? You know or why don't we take a moment to think about
what we're doing and why this was not actually accomplishing what you thought it would. Right? So so I
I understand I have not read Dr.
Jesus' book. I'll just say that. But I understand the idea of beauty first, right? Because the point
that he's trying to make is how do you change souls? How do you change souls? Which is, you know,
ultimately the goal, right? As Christians. But at the same time, if someone has, you know,
a loaded gun in his hand and is blowing people away, the first thing to do is stop him,
Right? And so you know, with regard to
I do think that it's appropriate that they'd be laws against abortion.
Now, I'm not a politician, I'm not a doctor, I'm not a maker of laws,
not a legislator. And so I can't,
I don't have the ability to say what the best kind of law about it would be.
There's a lot of opinions about that. Right? But I definitely believe that it's appropriate for laws to be passed against abortion.
I don't know if that answers your question, but
But yeah, I think it's it's it's like for instance, you know like one of the big accusations is sometimes pro
lifeers get here in the US is they'll say, oh, you're just pro-birth. You don't care about women.
You don't care about children, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, which is a huge lie. Almost all of the
pro-life activists that I know are actually very strongly engaged in helping people deal with all
kinds of other related problems, you know. But even if someone was just trying to prevent
children from being killed in the womb, I think that's pretty laudable, you know.
like someone is just
trying to address one kind of evil. That doesn't mean they don't care about other evils, right?
But, but yeah, so anyway, I don't know, Father Steven, you want to weigh in on into this?
Yes. Get ready for attempt to get myself canceled number 27.
I think this whole discussion is framed incorrectly. And I think it reveals deep pathology
in American society.
Oh, yes.
So on one hand, this will be the less controversial part.
Let me talk to our red lip friends.
So they're not listening to this podcast.
You never know.
Yeah, that's true.
And let me, you know, part of this is just asking questions that don't get asked.
Right.
So if we take their assertion, for example, at face value that a-
portion is healthcare, right? Why is that the only form of healthcare that they want to pursue,
to be available at no cost to poor women and women of color in this country?
If your pro-choice doesn't that require you to give people multiple choices, not just one?
Yeah. And don't talk to me about rights because we all know that every bourgeois,
Wait.
woman in this country has always been and will always be able to get an abortion if she wants it.
So they're not fighting for the rights for those people to get abortions. They're fighting
for poor women and women in color who get pregnant to have precisely one option and that's to get
an abortion. And they use, and this is both sides, both sides use every lever of shame and humiliation
this culture has to offer against poor women who get pregnant.
calling them welfare moms, calling them leeches, calling them lazy. Right? Our culture does not value
children. Our culture views children as a luxury item. That certain people of a certain social
standing from a certain cultural background get to have. And if other people dare to, right,
they're creating a societal problem. And the answer to that problem for our red lib friends
is to kill the child.
Right.
Now here's the part that may get me more canceled.
No.
The other side sees making abortion illegal as the solution to the problem.
Right.
And I know lots of people who do lots of things for charity.
I know lots of people even who have adopted children and they're doing good things and those
are wonderful things, but those don't solve the problem.
You can't adopt all the kids.
Right.
charity donation.
and cannot pay for prenatal and postnatal care
for every pregnant woman in this country who can't afford it.
So if you want to actually solve the problem from either side,
we have to make systemic changes in this country
and in our culture so that we value children
and we value families.
And so every pregnancy is not just okay,
is not just unable to be terminated,
but is actually valued and loved by the whole culture,
the whole community.
Such them.
We're willing to sacrifice something.
I'm willing to sacrifice something.
We're all collectively willing to sacrifice something
to try to help this child come into the world.
And we're rather than shaming this mother who dare to get pregnant.
We're going to honor her and protect her and help her again
on a systemic basis across the board, not just me doing this
with one person.
That's a good start, but it's not enough.
And if we did that, if we made those changes in this country,
abortion literally would not
be an issue because number one, there'd be no demand for it or almost none.
And what little demand there was, we could probably safely deny at that point.
So I think we approach the whole issue in the wrong way.
Arguing about whether it should be illegal or illegal or illegal for me is the wrong
question.
We have to examine the pathology in our society that has led to us having the abortion
right now and try and do something to fix it.
There's my-
Well, I mean, as the grand inquisitor of ancient faith ministries, I'm not going to cancel that. I agree that we're seeing work. So there's a bite there.
Well, tough.
I don't know if any of that's helpful to you, Cameron.
I hope so.
But I think rant aside, I think that's what that kind of beauty and truth approach means.
Yeah.
Seeing the child in the womb as beautiful. Right?
Yeah, and wanting to protect and nurture it and the mother and all of us coming together to nurture the child
I don't think that either
Telling the woman who can't afford to have a child to kill it or just saying yeah, you can't kill it
Right and hopefully you'll come into contact with someone like me who will try to help you
Maybe maybe not. I don't think either of those really do the job and I don't think they're based in beauty or truth ones based on
trying to punish injustice.
And the other one is based on basically wanting to sweep a problem under the rock.
Yeah.
Well, does that help Cameron?
Yeah, that's great. Thanks, Father.
Awesome. Awesome. Thank God.
All right. Well, we got.
I could tell you.
No.
No, you know, Canadians are always that polite.
That's just required.
Okay. Yeah. Oh yeah. Yeah.
All right, we've got Jack calling.
You get to follow that, Jack.
Yeah, from North Carolina.
So Jack, good to hear from someone from the old North state.
Indeed.
All right.
Well, I lived in North Carolina for 11 years.
So you have my attention.
It's a wonderful state.
It is.
Thank you for taking like all.
So my question for you guys tonight is
sort of about the role of doctrine in the church.
You guys have spoken a lot about,
I guess the matter of intellectual understanding
and your discussion of the Bible and so on.
And sometimes to me, it seems like you guys are,
I'm not trying to discredit you guys or anything,
but at some time.
comes across as, oh, doctrine is secondary to the life of the church or living the life in Christ.
And I understand that because you have the matter of if someone like a child or someone who is
mentally incapable of understanding things like doctrine or reading the texts of the church and
understanding them and so on. So I guess my question is for you guys, what is the role of doctrine
in the church and of understanding the faith.
It's a good question.
And I will say this to my own, not to just refute what you said.
But I do have to point out that in my first book, like the first chapter is literally
titled, Doctor in Matters.
So, I feel like I'm on record as saying that Doctor in Matters literally.
But the question is, how does it matter?
And what way does it matter, right?
So I found a, there's an essay, and I'm blanking on the title of it now, but there's an essay by Father George Florowski,
in which he talks about three levels, and he says that they're very interrelated and that the lines between them are not,
the borders between them are not super clear.
But he talks about three levels.
He talks about dogma, doctrine, and theology.
Okay. So
And the way that he defines them as dogma is those things that there really is zero compromising on right
These are the things that are the sine qua non. This is what the church believes, right? This is what the church you know
The core things that it that the church believes and teaches
doctrine is the way that you teach dogma
So that can have some variation right there are different ways of teaching the same dogma
As long as it's the same dogma that's acceptable and then theology is
is reflection and application of these things.
This is essentially the way the Florosky defines these things.
And I think that, while those are not absolute definitions
and he says that,
I think that that's a useful way of thinking about it, right?
So, you know,
one clue to this is, for instance, in Acts chapter 15,
that's right, isn't that when the Apostolic Council
happens, Father, Acts 15?
Yes.
Yeah.
the decrees that they give, it actually says this in the scripture, the word that's used is the
dogmas, the dogmas of the apostles that are distributed, that are passed around, and don't engage
in idolatry, don't engage in sexual immorality. And this is their dogma. This is the first dogma
in terms of a consulior dogma. And it's precisely instructions on things to do.
you. Right. And.
The way that dogmas that we might think of as being more conceptual,
like that, okay, Christ is fully God, fully man, one person in two natures,
the kind of calcedonian formula.
Some people will look at that and sort of draw that out from this question of things that you should do.
The reason why that matters and the way that it gets applied is especially in the way that we worship,
and the way that we pray.
Right, so like the example, one of the examples I gave is if you have a really wrong
belief about somebody. Let's say you think that I'm a pathological liar. If you believe that,
that everything I say is a lie, that I'm just constantly trying to deceive you, then the way that
you relate to me is going to be different from if you didn't believe that. Whether your belief about
me is true or not, it's going to alter the way that you relate to me. And so if we have wrong
beliefs about who God is, that can't alter the way that we relate to him. Right? So that's one of
of the ways in which doctrine applies in the Church.
But in many ways,
It depends on which doctrine you're talking about.
So the doctrine that the Eucharist is truly the body and blood of Christ, that gets applied
in another kind of way.
There's multiple ways it gets applied.
For instance, the way that the priest and the deacon clean up after the divine liturgy
is one of the ways that they get supplied.
The way that people receive Holy Communion is another way that gets applied.
So it is...
Absolutely, we believe the doctrine matters.
But at the same time, we should say that the reason why it matters is because of how it
affects what you do.
And the reason why we know that that's why it matters is because, as a says in scripture,
that Christ is going to judge every man according to his works, according to his deeds, according
to what he is doing.
It does not say that Christ is coming to judge every man according to his correct opinions.
is your input?
because they affect what you do, right? So that's what I would say in response to that.
Absolutely doctrine matters. But the reason that it matters is because it actually has real
actually has practical effects. It's not just because of a sort of set of theories,
you know, that you have to get it right. It's about doing right. And that's why doctrine matters
is because it affects what you do.
It's the-
sort of the roadmap for what you do.
Father, Steven, do you want to add to that or whatever?
Yeah, I, so I approached that from kind of a different angle
in that it has to do with the idea of the relationship
between ideas and practices.
And we as modern Western people tend generally
to be kind of idealists in the sense that we
see ID
is coming first and then those ideas being implemented in praxis.
Right.
And the truth is actually the exact opposite.
Ideas emerge from praxis, from practices.
The practices come first.
So, rituals come first, then beliefs emerge out of those.
And so, in the same way that the actual practice and worship and life in Christ
in Christ comes first.
doctrines emerge from that. And as they emerge from that, they serve to codify, to protect, to guard,
right, to further define that, and preserve that practice in that way of life, right,
to potential threats to that way of life. Yeah. I was going to say what I'll add to what you're saying,
just to add another piece of context to that and this is one of the things that I
observed, I'm sure you've observed it too, is that conviction follows conditioning. Right.
That people tend to hold fast and believe strongly about things because they've been engaging in it,
rather than the other way around, you know, in terms of the way that the human actually functions.
Like if you go to a certain kind of church all the time, you're going to tend to believe that
that that's the place you should be. And you're going to have all kinds of arguments
as to why it's the true true.
or wise, the right church or whatever it might be.
You know, so yeah, I mean, I absolutely agree with you,
Father, by the way, I should say.
And I don't think you were disagreeing with me, but from another angle.
Like I said, yeah, yeah.
And so if you look at, for example, Christian communities outside the Orthodox Church
that we would say have kind of gone off the rails, right?
They don't change their doctrine first and then implement the change doctrine in practice.
in practice. It goes
the exact opposite way. They change their practice. They change their practice. They change
who they are, or they change how they worship or they change. Those happen first. And then
over time, the doctrinal changes emerge as a result of the change of worship, the change
of practice. Right. The change of their view of the ministry changes because they change
to they are day, not night, vice versa.
And so this is very important when we're at...
addressing, for example, some of our red lip friends who are in the Orthodox Church, who
will, for example, say, well, doctrine, we're to love everyone. Love your neighbor is yourself.
We share the love of God. This is what we're about. They take this idea and they say, so doesn't
that mean we should change our practice here, there, what we consider as sin, what we do here and there.
Right. And see their
seeding on that idealistic basis.
They're trying to argue from the idea to the praxis.
But the truth is that our understanding of what God's love is
and what love for neighbor is
is something that emerges out of our collective experience
of God, right?
We know what love is because we've experienced
Christ's love of us.
Yeah.
That's the love that we're called to show to other people.
So what love is is defined through our praxis.
And so it can never be pitted against our praxis.
Right?
Yeah, because it comes out there.
Yeah, I mean, relatedly, like this is another thing
that Florovsky said, he said that charity,
which is good old fashioned word for love, right?
Charity should never be set against truth.
That these are not opposing things.
you know becoming
more dedicated to truth should not make you more uncharitable, becoming more charitable
should not make you not care about truth. That really, because Christ is the one who is,
you know, God is love and Christ is the truth, right? So it's all one. You can't pull things
out and say, we'll do this and then we don't have to worry about that, you know? So, does
that help Jack?
Yes, it does.
And just to be clear,
I wasn't trying to throw any accusations.
I.
I'm a big fan of orthodoxy and heterodoxy and I knew that you care about that and
hold to that. I just was expressing some confusion and I think this is very helpful.
No, I took that as seen now I was about to make a basketball reference and I've completely lost
what what you call it when someone passes the ball so that someone else can duck. He's not
the sports ball. I don't know the sports balls. Yeah. Yeah.
That's how I took it. Whatever whatever the word for that is.
So anyway, well thank you for calling Jack from North Carolina.
We're going to take one more call and then we're going to wrap up this Q&A episode.
So we have we have Nicholas calling all the way from the other coast.
So Nicholas, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Final call, make it good man.
pleasure to be on Father's up to listening for
Last several months, I, one of your episodes said to go back and start from the beginning.
So, I'm finally caught up in listening life.
All right.
But anyway, my question, I come from a Protestant background that was very much in very evangelistic
are using the
same methodology as Ray Comfort from the way of the master
series. I'm not sure if either of you are familiar with that.
Vagley.
Well, my question really was as Orthodox Christians, what
would be a good approach to evangelism, whether to
head.
or non-Christian in general.
Yeah, this is another, someone just told me that the word I was looking for, the basketball
word, those looking for was assist.
He assist.
So I will take this as another assist, because this is one of my big obsessions, his evangelism.
My initial response to that will be to say it depends.
It depends, right?
It depends not on whether or not you should evangelize.
We should be evangelizing, should be preaching the gospel, right?
The question is how do you do it best in the context you're in, right?
So there are some people that are much more open to hearing the gospel than others.
And there's some people you're going to need to express it in a particular way.
And then there's other people who can express it in another way.
I will tell you that I do
think that there are some approaches that the Orthodox at least in the English
speaking world have been using for a while now that I don't think are a good idea
or maybe not a good idea anymore. Right? And like one of those approaches is
okay let's try to evangelize evangelicals by telling them that we are the one true
church. And so you know you want to be in the one true church don't you? Where
it? So come on. Now that is not to say I do not believe that the Orthodox church
is not truly uniquely the true.
I believe that. I very much believe that.
But often the way that that sort of evangelistic pitch gets,
it's expressed is in terms of,
we're the best and don't you want to be in the best, right?
Or we're right and by definition, everyone else is wrong.
You know, and it becomes about being right.
Don't you want to come be right?
But as we said earlier, we're not going to be judged.
in the end by how rightly we were, we're going to be judged by what we did. We're going to be judged by if we're faithful to Christ.
Right. And so I think this approach of this sort of appeal to authority is is is is is not not a good idea.
Even though of course it did, you know, there are many people who became Orthodox because they were searching for the true church and here's the true church.
And I would not knock anybody who, if that's there, was their path. That was certainly a...
major element in my path. I wanted something that was true, the truth, right? But it can
be easy to get so attached to the idea of being right that one loses sight of Jesus Christ
himself. Who is the truth? You know? And so I believe that preaching in the gospel means
whatever, whatever, wherever you have to express it or whatever the context is, the gospel
is who is Jesus Christ? What?
What did he accomplish and what does he expect from us?
That's the gospel, those three things.
And then the response to that is, well, what do I have to do to be saved?
Like, how do I get on board with that?
And then, you know, we tell people exactly what it says in the scripture, repent and be
baptized, become part of the church, live the life of faithfulness.
That's the response to the gospel.
But the gospel is fundamentally about who Jesus Christ is, what he accomplished and what
does he expect from us.
That's what the gospel is.
You can express it differently with different people.
If you're talking to someone who's a Christian already, you can probably use the Scripture very plentifully, and they'll be on board with that because Christians respect the Scripture.
That's part of what it means to be a Christian. If you're talking to someone who isn't a Christian yet, then you can't just say, well, the Bible says this because they don't have any particular reason to believe the Bible.
Right. Now, you might show them what it says from Scripture and say, well, this expresses what I'm trying to tell you.
But you can't just say, well, the Bible says it, so you have to believe it because there's no reason that they're going to agree with it.
that right? So you have to see where a person is. What does he already believe? Everybody
has spiritual beliefs of some kind, you know, even if it's just I believe that these things
are right and these things are wrong. That's a spiritual set of beliefs. But it depends, it depends
a lot on who you're talking to and what their particular context is like the way that I would
talk to a negro pagan is very different from the way that I would talk to someone who's raised
going to an episcopal church for the first five years of their life and hasn't been back ever since.
Those are two very different religious worlds that those people are in.
So, yeah, it, like I said, it just depends.
And I think the biggest thing is that people who become Orthodox Christians out of a particular
community, that they are probably going to be the most capable of speaking to that community,
but they're going to need to go through some maturing in order to be able to do it in a
way that's going to be healthy and good for everybody involved and not just be about
Convencing other
people that they're right can come be right with me. So that's my little rant about preaching
the gospel. Father Steven. Yeah, and obviously evangelism requires preaching the gospel.
It is not like an optional part. Yeah. But it also has to take place within a frame, right?
as much as father Andrew would like the royalties.
Going around and handing out.
copies of a rhizocod or leaving them in public bathrooms.
Isn't gonna do the trick.
No, that's not evangelism.
It's not the couple, let's just try buying 10,000 copies
and seeing what happens first.
Planta fake seed with Father Andrew David.
I don't know, okay.
See what happens.
No, don't really.
So I church you to Rod Parsley, the person.
That is the worst thing you could turn me into. There's a whole frame though surrounding
that conversation about the gospel. And that frame is, I'm not going to say more important,
but it's just as important. Right. Because as Father Andrew said, yeah, they have to have
a reason to listen to the Bible. They also have a reason to listen to you. Yeah.
Yeah.
And
You know, you look at St. Hermann when he goes to the illusions in Alaska, right?
He does translate the scriptures, the services, the prayers, right?
But he doesn't just do that and like hand them out, right?
He also goes and he lived among them and learned their language, right?
And became a part of their community, right?
we didn't just
do that either. You also translated the scriptures and the verses of the prayers, right? Those
things have to go together, right? And, you know, you'll sometimes hear, so we're Protestant
friends, talk about being a Christian in public. And unfortunately, when they describe what
that means, it sounds an awful lot like the stuff Jesus used to condemn the Pharisees for
doing, right? Like standing on streetcorders and saying loud, long prayers, or do we get
the cracker barrel wherever you do it.
It's no kind of the same thing.
Wearing the tassels, you know, we can say wearing the Christian t-shirts, you know, half of which are semi-blastphemous anyway.
I'm trying to be clever.
Right, those kind of things, that's not being a Christian in public.
Right? Being a Christian in public is
living your life the way you're supposed to be living it, for example, when you're in the workplace.
Being humble, being kind, being compassionate.
right not joining in the
gossip not joining in picking on and belittling people, not joining in resentment
against the boss, right? Being a Christian in the sense of following Christ in
that place, right? And that kind of living among people and being a Christian
is what then gives you the opportunity to do the key thing which is to express
the gospel to someone who might then be willing to listen to you.
about it, right, who might be willing to hear that from you and might not just assume
you're trying to sell them amway or some other.
Okay, I'm not going to say this about anyway, or a pyramid scheme, which I am not saying
amway is.
Though their organization has a peak at the top, but it's broader at the bottom.
Definitely not saying it is, but more of a ziggurat, right, or Mary K. Cosmetics or whatever,
right? You're not trying to sell them on something. You're not...
recruiting for your group, right?
But you've shared part of your life with them.
And now you're offering to share more of it.
That's a very different thing
than trying to sell somebody something.
Is that illuminating Nicholas?
Very much so, fathers makes a lot of sense.
And would you, would either of you have any idea
reading assignment for me and anyone else listening maybe from church
fathers or boy it was about to recommend his old book that you said no no I won't
do that I'm not gonna do that I'm not even a church-weird uncle
Um, um,
Yeah, I mean, I think I think that honestly this might sound weird, but I think that saints lives, especially missionary saints
Is is the way to go on on this question, right because they're showing you what it looks like to be evangelistic in particular
Contexts I mean starting with the axiom apostles the first collection of saints lives all about evangelism
Right.
So, I mean, that's where I would go.
Yeah, and their missionary work
is not incidental to their st.hood.
Right, right.
We don't recommend this because we'll see the saints,
they're really good people,
they're really spiritually wise people.
So, whatever they do,
they're doing it the right way.
That's not the perspective of this.
They became saints.
They came to know Christ more deeply.
They became...
holy. They came close to God. They became like Christ through their missionary work. Yeah.
To which they were called. That was the path they followed to find their salvation. Right.
And so how they did it and what they did is not just this incidental thing that sort of
baptize or blessed or made more authoritative by them being the same. But it is actual,
actually their participation what
is God is doing and it shows us
then how we can
and also work out our own salvation
by following a similar path in our own time and place.
Yeah.
What do you think, can you follow that assignment, Nicholas?
Yeah, I think I can.
I think Herman is actually the patron of our parish.
He's a good one.
And my parents used to do AM way.
Oh man.
No offense.
That's not taken.
Andway bought him his breakfast cereal in the morning father, Stephen.
Come on.
And my vitamin and your vitamins.
You're going to take vitamins out of his childhood.
Come on.
Anyway, he said they used to sell it.
Used to.
Yeah.
Well, you know, time and space are an illusion.
So anyway, well, thank you very much for calling Nicholas.
We appreciate it.
Yes.
Thank you, fathers.
You're welcome. All right. Well, that wraps up this special
Second anniversary Q&A episode. We hope you've enjoyed all of our memories that we've played in the past and thank you everyone for calling
That's our show for tonight. Thank you for listening if you didn't get through to us live this time
We'd select to hear from you. You can email us at Lord of Spirits and Ancient Faith.com
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com
slash Lord of Spirits
and join us for...
our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific,
except next time when there will be something special.
Yes, and if you're on Facebook, you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave
reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, please share the show with a friend, word
of mouth, word of mouth, share it with your friends that are going to love it, people
who are going to be astonished by it, or even bored by it.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com Stroke Support.
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air. That's all the AFR podcasters. You can't pick it shoes.
That's right. Thank you. Good night.
God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
and I'll be...
and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter five, verses 11 through 12.